<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The princess of Fess, or, The amours of the court of Morocco a novel : in two parts.</title>
            <author>Préchac, Jean de, 1647?-1720.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 138 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 76 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90934</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3207B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42537</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">36282263</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 36282263</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150170</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90934)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150170)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2234:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The princess of Fess, or, The amours of the court of Morocco a novel : in two parts.</title>
                  <author>Préchac, Jean de, 1647?-1720.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 143 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Bently, and M. Magnes ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Jean de Préchac by Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, tightly bound, and with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the William Andrews Clark Memorial Library, University of California, Los Angeles.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150170:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PRINCESS OF FESS: OR, THE AMOURS of the COURT of MOROCCO. A Novel.</p>
            <p>In Two Parts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Bently,</hi> and <hi>M. Magnes,</hi> in <hi>Ruſſel-ſtreet,</hi> in <hi>Covent-Garden,</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:150170:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150170:2"/>
            <head>TO HER GRACE The DUTCHESS of <hi>RICHMOND,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe Your Grace,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>NO ſooner was the Princeſs of <hi>Feſs</hi> ready to appear in publick on our <hi>Engliſh</hi> World, but ambitious to Kiſs Your Graces hands,
<pb facs="tcp:150170:3"/>ſhe is come to claim the protection of Your Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Name, not without all imaginable hopes of finding a favourable reception from that Perſon, whoſe quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are obſerv'd with ſuch admiration, by thoſe of the firſt rank in Vivacity of Wit and Profoundneſs of Judgment, who have Una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly voted, that it is as eaſie for the diſtreſſed to find a Sanctuary in the Arms of Your Graces ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Safeguard, as it is
<pb facs="tcp:150170:3"/>difficult to be ſupply'd with apt expreſſions to ſet forth Your Graces perfections.</p>
            <p>For my part, Madam, the Knowledge of my own difficiency has been a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign antidote againſt the vanity of endeavouring ſuch an <hi>Herculian</hi> labour on my own bottom, and of attempting thoſe impoſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and when I have gone to borrow from the moſt exquiſite of the Ancients Panegyricks, I have found all ſo ſhort from Your
<pb facs="tcp:150170:4"/>Graces Merits, that looking down with Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt on thoſe little things which the Modern Writers have uſed in the ſetting forth of Your Graces Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, I have avoyded the preſumption, and reſted Contented with the Honour of Subſcribing my ſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <hi>May it pleaſe Your Grace,</hi> 
               </salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Graces moſt Humble, and moſt Obedient Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,</hi>
P. BELLON</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:150170:4"/>
            <head>THE PRINCESS OF FESS.</head>
            <head type="sub">PART I.</head>
            <p>THE <hi>Arabian</hi> Empire has been one of the moſt flouriſhing of the World, both by the Duration and the Large Extent of it. Its Principal Seat was in <hi>Africa,</hi> though it has likewiſe poſſeſſed Large Territories in the other parts of the World.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:150170:5"/>It was not without divers conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable changes, that it Flouriſhed ſo long, and which have cauſed its decay; amongſt which, there happened an alteration about 150 years ſince, which for ſome time did raiſe their Reputation.</p>
            <p>The Family of the <hi>Benimerignis</hi> having enjoy'd the Throne for a long time, and poſſeſſed the Empire with Splendor and Dignity, did thereby reſtore unto it that Luſtre in which it had formerly been under the <hi>Almanzors:</hi> But having at laſt torn one another in pieces through Partialities, they were driven from thence, in the beginning of the late Age, by the <hi>Cherifs;</hi> which name is aſſumed by all thoſe that pretend to be of Kin unto <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met,</hi> and is of great uſe to thoſe that bear it, to attract the venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that People who are the moſt ſuperſtitious of the World.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Cherifs</hi> having rendred themſelves formidable by that Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:150170:5"/>War which they made againſt the <hi>Portugais,</hi> and having almoſt driven them out of <hi>Africa,</hi> they gained ſo much the Love of theſe Nations, that they eaſily did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the <hi>Benimerignis,</hi> which were then the Maſters of <hi>Mauritania,</hi> and they poſſeſſed themſelves alſo of divers other Parts of <hi>Africa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mahomet Cherif</hi> did reunite all their former Authority in his own Perſon, and did enjoy, even unto an extream old Age, one of the greateſt Empires of the World. His Succeſſors had eaſily preſerved it, if they had not had more than Foreign Enemies to Combate: But being at variance amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that vaſt Empire was in our time divided into ſeveral Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels. <hi>Feſs,</hi> which had been the chief City of the whole Empire, had its particular Kings, which were not acknowledged by the reſt of <hi>Africa: Morocco</hi> had its Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigns; the Kingdoms of <hi>Tremeſon,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:150170:6"/>of <hi>Suſs,</hi> and of <hi>Tarudant,</hi> had theirs alſo, and acknowledged none other: And in a Word, divers Pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Princes did poſſeſs all thoſe vaſt Territories, which in former times yielded obedience but unto one only.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bembuca</hi> King of <hi>Feſs,</hi> and <hi>Gayland</hi> Prince of <hi>Suſs,</hi> had rendred them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves formidable to all the others, through that Bloody War which they made againſt their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, or through the Jars which they had betwixt themſelves, which they always decided by Arms, and the advantage of which did fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently remain on <hi>Bembuca</hi>'s ſide. Though <hi>Bembuca</hi> was extream Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el towards his Enemies, there ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was a more kind Father. The Prince of <hi>Feſs,</hi> and the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs <hi>Alzira,</hi> his Children, were ſo dear unto him, that he would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually have them in his preſence, and it was with great difficulty that he would bear their abſence
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:150170:6"/>ſome hours of the day in order to their Education: He would never grant any requeſts but at the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of one or the other of them; and moſt particularly at the recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of <hi>Alzira,</hi> who always employ'd her ſelf in the behalf of the unfortunate. She had a deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate and an advantageous Shape. Her Eyes were blew and full, her Air was Majeſtick, mixed with ſtore of Sweetneſs, and with ſuch inſinuating Actions, that it was impoſſible to behold her without ſome concern for her Perſon. Her Beauty, which made a great noiſe throughout all <hi>Africa,</hi> had already ingaged divers Princes to demand her of her Father, who not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to reſolve on the abſence of a Daughter ſo lovely as his, did always avoid the Marrying of her, under the pretence, that he belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved her yet too Young. <hi>Gayland</hi> would once have Wedded her himſelf, but there was ſo little pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:150170:7"/>betwixt the Ages of <hi>Alzi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> and of that Prince, who had been Marryed twice before, that <hi>Bembuca</hi> had rejected the Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals with anger; which contempt had contributed very much in the renewing of the War between thoſe two Princes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gayland,</hi> who was Childleſs, had a Young Prince of the Houſe of the <hi>Cherifs,</hi> a Kinſman of his, brought up at his Court, who had an equal right on the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Feſs,</hi> and on the Principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Suſs.</hi> At firſt he had not taken care of his Education, but to have one day a pretence to drive <hi>Bembuca</hi> out of the Kingdom of <hi>Feſs,</hi> if at any time he ſhould get an advantage over him by force of Arms. But <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> (that was the name of the Young <hi>Cherif</hi>) had ſomething ſo admirable in his Perſon, and had rendred himſelf ſo complaiſant to all <hi>Gayland</hi>'s deſires, that he had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely won his favour. Never
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:150170:7"/>had any Prince a more piercing Wit, a Mind more bent unto great Enterpriſes, and who did more paſſionatly love Arms. <hi>Gay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> who did ſometimes ſend him into the Field, was ſurpriſed to to hear him diſcourſe on all the particulars thereof, with the ſame exactneſs as an experimented Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander would do. He had been brought up in ſo great an aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion againſt <hi>Bembuca,</hi> that he was continually diſcourſing of the means which he ſhould uſe to drive away that Uſurper. And being very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous of knowledge, he would take great delight in entertaining of Strangers. A certain <hi>Engliſh</hi> Captive, named <hi>Talbor,</hi> had ſo well taken his meaſures on his Princes Curioſity, that he was preferr'd by him in his converſation before all others. <hi>Talbor</hi> would never ſpeak to him but of Armies, of Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar-pieces, Grenados, Canons, and generally of all thoſe things that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:150170:8"/>the Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> uſe in War. He would inform him, that for the eafie taking of a place, it was requiſite to know both the Strength and Weakneſs of it, to attaque it at thoſe places which were the eafieſt to overcome. <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> did take a fingular delight in hearing the Slaves reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and in reducing all that he ſaid unto thoſe deſigns, and to that hatred which he had againſt <hi>Bembuca;</hi> he fancied that if he could ſee the Fortifications of the City of <hi>Feſs,</hi> which was Capital of the Kingdom of that name, he ſhould have the leſs difficulties in rendring himſelf Maſter of it, whenever he ſhould beſiege it, as he hoped he ſhould one day. He ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed to <hi>Talbor</hi> the extream deſire which he had to go in a diſguiſe to <hi>Feſs,</hi> with him, and obſerve that City. <hi>Talbor</hi> would have diſwaded him, telling him, that without expoſing of himſelf unto the ſucceſs of an
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:150170:8"/>Enterpriſe ſo dangerous as that, it would not be hard to get a Draught of that Place, and to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve all its defects. But <hi>Ali Hamet,</hi> who did not comprehend how that could be done on paper, gave the Slave to underſtand, that the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs was of ſuch a concern as would invite him to ſee the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of it with his own Eyes, though there were never ſo much danger in the enterpriſe. <hi>Talbor</hi> durſt not contradict him any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. The next day <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> abſented himſelf from his Uncle, under other pretences, and having diſguiſed himſelf in a mean habit, he ſet forwards towards <hi>Feſs,</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by <hi>Talbor,</hi> and a <hi>Marabout,</hi> (thoſe are <hi>Mahometan Monks,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whoſe ſafeguard one may tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel with great ſafety.) After a long march they arrived at <hi>Feſs,</hi> where <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> did apply himſelf with a World of diligence to obſerve the Situation of that City, and thoſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:150170:9"/>Poſts that were fortified. He was walking on the <hi>Rampart,</hi> when there paſſed by him a certain kind of Chariot, drawn by <hi>Arabian</hi> Horſes. The Prince having obſerved ſome Ladies in it magnificently dreſſed, had the curioſity to ſee their Faces, but it was impoſſible for him to have that ſatisfaction, by reaſon of the diſtance, and that the Ladies had their Backs turn'd towards him; he contented himſelf with following them at a diſtance. Scarce had he made Twenty ſteps for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, when he heard a great noiſe of confuſed voices, which obliged him to double his pace towards the Chariot. Lions are very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon at <hi>Feſs,</hi> and divers perſons keep of them: One of the biggeſt ſize had broke looſe from his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Houſe, and was walking qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly on the <hi>Rampart,</hi> as the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot was going by; the Horſes were affrighted at it, and ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a running, notwithſtanding
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:150170:9"/>all that the Coachman could do to ſtop them. The Lyon percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them to run, failed not to follow. A company of People, who knew the nature of Lyons, who equally become furious, when they are purſued, or that they ſee any thing to flie before them, did cry out at a diſtance, to have the driver ſtop his Horſes. Mean time the Chariot was overturned, and the Lyon was already ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing his fury on the Horſes, not one perſon daring to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach near him; when that <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> came up, who ſeeing fear and diſpair ſpread over the Ladies Faces, did preſently go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to aſſiſt them all; and having perceived that there was one which was eaſily to be diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the reſt by her beauty and the magnificency of her dreſs, he buſied himſelf chiefly in ſetting her our of danger. But the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot was overturned in ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:150170:10"/>that it was impoſſble to aſſiſt her, without expoſing her to the fury of the Lyon. <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> in that extreamity conſulted nothing but his Courage; and having drawn his Cimiter, he attaqued the Lyon with great Valour, and with a blow of his Cimiter he wounded him very dangerouſly on the Head. The Lyon roaring with rage, was going to tear in pieces the Perſon that had wounded him: But <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> not being daunted, did courageouſly reſiſt him, and wounded him in ſo many different places, that he put him out of Combate.</p>
            <p>After this happy ſucceſs, he drew near unto that Lady who had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared ſo beautiful to him, and lent her his Hand to help her out of that place. The Lady, who was already ſtruck with aſtoniſhment at the ſurpriſing Valour of her Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer, had then leaſure to admire his good meen, and to return him
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:150170:10"/>thanks in terms that were full of acknowledgments. <hi>Ali Hamet,</hi> who had never ſeen ſo beautiful a Perſon, did at that inſtant feel ſome ceratin motions, of which he had been ignorant all his life time. A great number of Perſons of all ſorts and conditions that came thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, gave <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> to underſtand, that ſhe who he had ſo happily reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cued was the Princeſs of <hi>Feſs,</hi> which obliged him to behold her again with the more attention: But he enjoyed not long that pleaſure, for <hi>Alzira</hi> was in an inſtant encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed round with Ladies, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted her back to the Palace to conſolate <hi>Bembuca,</hi> who had new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly been advertiſed of that misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune. <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> was in ſo great an admiration at the ſurpriſing Beauty of the Princeſs, that he mixed himſelf with the Crowd of thoſe that follow'd, ſcarce knowing what he was doing. <hi>Talbor,</hi> who had not had his Eyes off of him, fore-ſeeing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:150170:11"/>that <hi>Bembuca</hi> would cauſe a ſearch to be made after that Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that had rendred ſo great a Service to his Daughter, did ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe him to retire in haſte, leſt he ſhould be known. The Prince was unwilling, as having no mind to diſtance himſelf from the charming <hi>Alzira,</hi> who he hoped to ſee again. But <hi>Talbor</hi> did ſo well repreſent to him thoſe Evils which he was to fear if <hi>Bembuca</hi> ſhould come to know him, that his Love, which was but juſt budding, had not power ſufficient to hinder him from following the Counſels of his faithful Slave. They went to rejoin the <hi>Marabout,</hi> who was ſtaying for them at the City Gates, and got away from <hi>Feſs</hi> with great diligence. Mean time <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zira,</hi> who had her Idea fill'd with her generous Protector, and who did already feel in her ſelf ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more than a bare acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment, did conjure her Father
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:150170:11"/>to ſend for him, and give him a recompence ſuitable to that ſervice which he had ſo lately rendred her. <hi>Bembuca,</hi> who deſired to know ſo Valiant a Perſon, gave orders for a ſearch. His cares were fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, no body knew him, and though that all thoſe who had ſeen the Combate, did ſpeak of him with admiration, there was not one found that knew who he was. New perquiſitions were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain made, but ſtill with the ſame ſucceſs. Mean time there being daily ſome new circumſtance of his Valour mentioned, that buſineſs did much contribute to attract the Veneration of the People on <hi>Bem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buca,</hi> and his Family; for he had the ſubtilty to publiſh, that their Prophet <hi>Mahomet,</hi> perceiving a Princeſs of the Blood of the <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifs,</hi> and his Relation, in ſo eminent a danger, he had come in Perſon himſelf to deliver her, and had diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appeared preſently after ſo brave an
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:150170:12"/>Action. The People of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try are very ſuperſtitious; that made them give credit to the Story, the noiſe of which was preſently ſpread far and near, throughout all the Kingdom of <hi>Feſs,</hi> and all the World did ſpeak of it, as of a miracle. What Glory ſoever it was for the Princeſs to have been aſſiſted by the pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Prophet, her Heart had ſome repugnancy to believe the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick opinion; and every time that ſhe did reflect on the good meen of her Deliverer, ſhe did wiſh, at leaſt, that there were ſome Mortal that did reſemble him; while that her Modeſty did oblige her to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal her reſentments. But when ſhe was in private with <hi>Balabai</hi> (who was one of her Women that ſhe much affected) <hi>Balabai</hi> made no difficulty to own, that ſhe had rather have ow'd her life unto ſome <hi>African</hi> Prince, than to the Great <hi>Mahomet.</hi> But <hi>Alzira,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:150170:12"/>who had her Mind continually fill'd with an Idea of the Strangers good meen, did not agree to that, and did ſo often repreſent his Picture after ſo advantageous a manner, that <hi>Balabai</hi> was obliged to acquieſs, that all the Princes of <hi>Africa</hi> did not come near in good meen unto him that had preſerved her life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ali Hamet,</hi> who was return'd to <hi>Suſs,</hi> did lead ſo private a life, that all the World were ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed at ſo ſudden a change. <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zira</hi>'s Beauty, thoſe Words which ſhe had ſaid to him, and a Charming and Majeſtick Air which he had never ſeen in any other Perſon, did continually come into his Mind. He delighted to be alone, that he might freely ſpend his thoughts on his ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Princeſs, and he continually did prefer the Slave <hi>Talbor</hi>'s con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation unto that of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Lords of <hi>Suſs.</hi> What a fatal
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:150170:13"/>Journey have we had, <hi>ſaid he to him?</hi> while I did deſign to have drawn from thence great advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges againſt <hi>Bembuca,</hi> I have loſt my ſelf. I love the Princeſs, I confeſs it to thee; but what will now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of me? <hi>Bembuca,</hi> who poſſeſſes a Throne that is mine, has doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs confirm'd her in ſentiments of hatred and averſion againſt me; ſo that I muſt never hope to make her ſenſible of my Love, ſeeing that I cannot ſo much as ſee her to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form her of it; ſhe will never hear any thing concerning me, but ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to my Glory or to my Shame; the one and the other are dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to me, and will equally draw her anger on me; for if I have any advantage over <hi>Bembuca,</hi> ſhe will doubtleſs hate the Enemy of her Father; and if I am vanquiſhed, ſhe will have a contempt for a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable Prince. <hi>Talbor</hi> did endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to comfort him, in repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that a Peace might be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:150170:13"/>in ſome ſhort time between the King of <hi>Feſs</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Suſs;</hi> and that he being of the Blood of the <hi>Cherifs,</hi> it might not be impoſſible but that he ſhould one day Eſpouſe the Princeſs of <hi>Feſs.</hi> But <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> did think his reaſons too weak, and too far fetch'd; he was for more practicable means where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to ſerve his Love. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he looked upon <hi>Talbor</hi> more as a Friend than a Slave, he did put him in mind, that ſeeing that he had been ingaged in the underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of this Voyage, which he durſt not call fatal, though he had loſt his liberty in it, he ought alſo to give him ſome expedients where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to inform the Princeſs of his paſſion. <hi>Talbor,</hi> who did find him to be deeply in Love, and who knew by experience what ſtrange diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bances Love does cauſe, did offer to go to <hi>Feſs,</hi> to introduce him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into <hi>Bembuca's</hi> favour, under pretence of teaching him the uſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:150170:14"/>of Fire Balls and Canons, and by thoſe means endeavour if it were poſſible, to inform the Princeſs of thoſe ſentiments which he had for her. <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> was ſo ſatisfied with that propoſition, that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd no longer the affranchiſing of <hi>Talbor,</hi> thereby to engage him the more to ſerve him, with the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter affection, towards <hi>Alzira.</hi> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that he had cauſed thoſe Paſſes to be diſpatched which were neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for the ſecurity of his Journey, he conjur'd him with Embraces not to ſpare either Care or Charges in giving him news of his Princeſs with all diligence imaginable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Talbor</hi> being arrived at <hi>Feſs,</hi> did endeavour to introduce himſelf at Court, giving out, that he had left the Service of a great Prince of <hi>Europe</hi> to apply himſelf unto <hi>Bembuca</hi>'s Service, whoſe Merit and Valour had been made known to him by an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Officer of <hi>Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gire,</hi> who had Sojourn'd for ſome
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:150170:14"/>time at <hi>Feſs.</hi> Such a probable diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe did preſently flatter <hi>Bem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buca</hi>'s Vanity: But thoſe experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which <hi>Talbor</hi> made in his preſence with Gun-powder, whoſe different and various effects were unknown to the <hi>Moors,</hi> did abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely incline him to take him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Service. The King deſired alſo that he ſhould make ſome Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>works to divert the Princeſs, who was become very Melancholy of late. Thoſe happy beginnings did make him hope that he ſhould ſhortly be in a condition to render ſome Services of importance unto <hi>Ali Hamet.</hi> Moſt part of Courti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers love Novelties; divers young Perſons of the Court did expreſs their great deſires to be acquainted with this Stranger. <hi>Talbor</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd their Wills with reſpect, and having obſerved that the reſt of the Gentry had ſome deference for a young Cavalier named <hi>Maucaden,</hi> he had the Curioſity to learn on
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:150170:15"/>what account; he was inform'd, that his own merits did much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute towards the receiving thoſe reſpects, and that he was alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd as being the Brother to <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labai,</hi> the Princeſs <hi>Alzira</hi>'s Favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite. That laſt reaſon did oblige <hi>Talbor</hi> to ſhew him a great reſpect. <hi>Maucaden</hi> did give him in ſundry occaſions ſome particular marks of his eſteem, and alſo promis'd to mention him to his Siſter. Which he performed ſo well, that his good Offices had like to have prov'd fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal to him: for <hi>Balabai,</hi> to oblige her Brother, did ſo highly extol <hi>Talbor</hi>'s good qualities to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, that ſhe deſired to have him in her Service. <hi>Alzira</hi> ſpoke of it to the King, who granted her that favour, and gave order that <hi>Talbor</hi> ſhould be made an <hi>Eunuque,</hi> that he might be in a condition to ſerve the Princeſs, becauſe that the <hi>Eunuques</hi> only have that privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. All thoſe mean ſorts of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:150170:15"/>perſons that envy thoſe ſorts of Emploies which put them in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of having great Preferments, and of raiſing their Friends and Relations, do patiently ſuffer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be made <hi>Eunuques,</hi> in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to thoſe great advantages that they hope from thence. <hi>Mauca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> having learned of his Siſter the reſolution which the King had taken of making <hi>Talbor</hi> ſo, to diſpoſe of him afterwards to the Princeſs, was willing to be the firſt that ſhould inform him of his good For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, and immediately went to joy him of it. <hi>Talbor</hi> extreamly ſurpriſed with a compliment of that nature, and ſo little expected, did intreat <hi>Maucaden</hi> to divert that evil from him, confeſſing that he had rather ſerve as a Slave in a Gally, than to be a Favorite in the Palace, ſeeing that there was no getting in by any other means than under thoſe cruel conditions which he had mentioned to him.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:150170:16"/>
               <hi>Maucaden</hi> ſurprz'd to hear him talk ſo, did tax him of Barbari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and told him, that though he himſelf was not ſenſible of that good which was offer'd him, he would make him happy even againſt his Will. But <hi>Talbor</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted at his pretended good Fortune, did ſo earneſtly intreat him to alter that reſolution, that <hi>Maucaden</hi> left him after he had told him, that ſeeing he had not ſufficiency of Ambition or of Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage to bear ſo great a Fortune, he would tell his Siſter that he had been deceived in that good opinion that he had had of him.</p>
            <p>While that <hi>Talbor</hi> was fearing thoſe fatal effects of his pretended good Fortune, the Prince <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> impatient in his Love, had taken the Field at the head of a great Body of Horſe, much leſs to gain a Conqueſt, than to take ſome Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, that might tell him ſome
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:150170:16"/>news of <hi>Alzira:</hi> His march did alarm <hi>Bembuca,</hi> who ſent divers Troops to oppoſe him. <hi>Mauca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> who had the command of them, did ask permiſſion to lead <hi>Talbor</hi> along with him, and by that means he ſaved him from that reſolution which had been taken of making him an <hi>Eunuque.</hi> He marched long Journeys, and in a ſhort time found himſelf near unto the Enemy. <hi>Ali Hamet,</hi> who was wholy taken up with his Love, and the deſign of taking ſome few Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, permitted his Troops to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh themſelves in a very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious Camp, and did march one whole Night at the head of ſome few Men, to obſerve the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, or peradventure, to more commodiouſly make ſome Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. But the Day Light having ſurpriſed him, he perceived that he had advanced too far, and found himſelf compaſſed about with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Squadrons of Enemies, without
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:150170:17"/>any poſſibility of retreat. That great number with which he was ſurrounded, did not hinder him from defending himſelf with an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imaginable Valour; yet he was taken, or rather over-powered than vanquiſhed. His Troops having been informed of his misfortune, they ſuddenly Disbanded them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and <hi>Maucaden</hi> returned to <hi>Feſs,</hi> to conduct thither in Perſon his Illuſtrious Priſoner. <hi>Talbor</hi> did avoid appearing before him, for fear of loſing himſelf, if it were perceived that he had formerly had ſome Commerce with <hi>Ali Hamet. Bembuca,</hi> who had always feared leaſt that <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> ſhould one Day drive him from the Throne, did learn with all the joy imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that he was made Priſoner. All his Grandees did Compliment him on that good ſucceſs, <hi>Alzira</hi> only appeared indifferent in the midſt of ſuch an univerſal joy; ſhe was not ſenſible of any thing, ſince
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:150170:17"/>the adventure of the Lyon, the Idea of her Deliverer had continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally remain'd in her mind; and though ſhe had been perſwaded that it was <hi>Mahomet</hi> who had rendred her that Signal piece of Service, ſhe ſtill pleas'd her ſelf, in thinking that ſhe would have Lov'd moſt paſſionatly ſome Prince that had been like her Deliverer. Theſe chimerical fancies did conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually poſſeſs her mind, and <hi>Balabai</hi> had all the pains imaginable to draw her out of them. Though <hi>Bembu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca</hi> had a mortal hatred againſt <hi>Ali Hamet,</hi> he ſeemingly treated him well, to let the People know, that he honour'd the Blood of the <hi>Cherifs,</hi> even in the perſon of his Enemy. He Lodged him in his own Palace, and order'd that all the honours which were uſed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Prince his Son, ſhould be rendred unto him alſo, and likewiſe deſired that <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> ſhould go make his Reverence to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:150170:18"/>the Queen and Princeſs. Mean time, <hi>Alzira</hi> was ſo oppreſſed with her continual reſtleſneſs of mind, that ſhe intreated her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to diſpence her from being at the Queens Appartment, when <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> ſhould go to Viſit her. But the whole Court ringing of his good meen with admiration, <hi>Balabai</hi> had the Curioſity to go to ſee him. <hi>Ali Hamet,</hi> who had hoped to ſee <hi>Alzira</hi> in the Queens preſence, and who thought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf already but too well recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penced for the loſs of his Liberty, did in vain ſeek her with his Eyes, and ſtay'd them on no Perſon, not finding out his moſt Charming Princeſs. He was ready to ask where ſhe was, but he durſt not give himſelf that ſatisfaction, for fear of being wanting in reſpect towards the Queen, or it may be leaſt that the particular intereſt that he ſhould expreſs for the Princeſs might be perceived.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:150170:18"/>Thoſe great reſpects which were rendred to <hi>Balabai,</hi> did ſet him in a doubt whether ſhe were not the Princeſs of <hi>Feſs;</hi> though he was well aſſur'd that it was not the ſame Perſon that had made him in Love. He retired himſelf from the Queens Appartment, in a much more reſtleſs mind than he had come thither. Sometimes he imagin'd that there was no other Princeſs of <hi>Feſs</hi> than <hi>Balibai;</hi> and a moment after he would repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to himſelf all thoſe Features of that lovely Perſon whom he had deliver'd from the fury of the Lyon, and did very well remember that all the People had treated her as a Princeſs. Finally, after divers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections, he believed that he had confounded that amiable Perſon with the Princeſs, and that doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it was ſome Woman of hers, whoſe extream Beauty had made him miſtake her for the Princeſs. But who ever it were, he did feel ſo
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:150170:19"/>ſtrong a paſſion for that perſon, that without troubling himſelf whether ſhe were a Princeſs or a Slave, he did Love her with an equal ardor, and did continually think of the means to ſee her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain</p>
            <p>Mean time <hi>Balabai,</hi> who had looked on <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> with great attention, had been ſo charmed with his good meen, that even from that very firſt ſight it was impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for her to reſiſt a certain ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency, that did engage her to love him almoſt againſt her Will. When ſhe came to <hi>Alzira,</hi> ſhe entertaind her with nothing but what did concern <hi>Ali Hamet;</hi> and as ſhe never did conceal any thing from the Princeſs, ſhe confeſs'd to her with bluſhes, that ſhe lov'd that Prince; and added, that ſhe ſtrongly fancied, that the good meen of her Deliverer, which ſhe ſo much praiſed, did come very near to that of <hi>Ali Hamet. Alzira,</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:150170:19"/>without making any reflection, did at the firſt chide her, for lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving her Fathers Enemy. But after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards believing that <hi>Balabai's</hi> Love would give her an occaſion of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taliating all thoſe Jeſts and Dro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leries which her favorite had made on the account of her melancholy, ſhe was not ſorry that ſhe ſhould love <hi>Ali Hamet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Love was the Subject of all their Converſations. <hi>Alzira</hi> had a moſt ſenſible pleaſure in frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpeaking of him who had ſav'd her life, and <hi>Balabai,</hi> whom love had rendred more diligent than ordinarily, did no longer reproach the Princeſs of that paſſion which ſhe had for a <hi>Chimera;</hi> and <hi>Alzira</hi> did in her turn make her confeſs, that there was much more weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in loving a Man by meer fancy, than in loving one unto whom great obligations are due. <hi>Balabai,</hi> not oppoſing her ſelf directly unto the Princeſs's ſentiments, did
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:150170:20"/>however inſinuate unto her, that a paſſion in which a heart does ingage it ſelf of its proper motion, is much ſtronger and more certain, than that in which an acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment had ſome ſhare, ſeeing that the one was an effect of inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, while that the other lay at the mercy of divers Accidents. The Princeſs did not wholly agree on that, and did maintain, that there never could be any love pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd by bare acknowledgments; that inclinations, had always a great ſhare in Love, but that perſons were willing to deceive themſelves, that the heart might have the leaſt ſhame in owning its own weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, under pretence that ſome ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgedment did force him to Love.</p>
            <p>Mean time, <hi>Talbor</hi> had found out a means privately to ſee <hi>Ali Hamet,</hi> and to let him know how much he was concern'd that he had not been capable of rendring
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:150170:20"/>him ſome Service towards the Princeſs, who did never ſee any but Women or <hi>Eunuques.</hi> The Prince was not ſurpriſed at it, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he himſelf, though lying in the Palace ſome days ſince, had never had any opportunity of ſeeing that Charming perſon, who had given him ſo much Love, for he no longer did believe that it was the Princeſs. He did every day walk in a certain Gallery of the Palace, much leſs to obſerve the Curious pieces of panting with which it was adorn'd, than to think without reſtraint, on his misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes. <hi>Balabai</hi> having taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of it, paſſed through that Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery, making as if it were her way to go into the Queens Appartment. She was very deſirous to ſpeak to <hi>Ali Hamet,</hi> and to ask him his Judgment on thoſe Pictures: But by ill fortune, he underſtood her not, and he ſpoke to her again in a Language that ſhe was ignorant
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:150170:21"/>of. Thoſe of <hi>Feſs</hi> ſpeak a Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage which is particular to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but thoſe of <hi>Tarudant</hi> and of <hi>Suſs</hi> ſpeak a corrupt <hi>Arabick.</hi> The Courtiers ſpeak <hi>Portugais,</hi> and for the moſt part the <hi>African</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces take a particular care to have their Children learn that Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. <hi>Balabai,</hi> who had propoſed to her ſelf this occaſion, of being informed whether one day <hi>Ali Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met</hi> ſhould become ſenſible to her Love, was in an extream anguiſh to find they underſtood not one another. Yet as all Lovers are apt to flatter themſelves, ſhe did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound to her advantage all the Princes Civilities, who remain'd in a comfortleſs condition for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving loſt ſo fair an opportunity of of clearing his doubt, if that that Perſon who would have ſpoken to him, were the Princeſs, and of learning whether that Perſon whom he had deliver'd from the Lyons fury were ſtill in the Palace. <hi>Bala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bai</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:150170:21"/>remembring that the Princeſs had learned <hi>Portugais</hi> from a Slave of that Nation, gave her an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of her late adventure, and did intreat her to ſerve her as an Interpreter, on this account. <hi>Alzi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> did at firſt excuſe her ſelf from it, expreſſing an averſion of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſing with her Fathers Enemy. But her Favorite did ſo well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent to her how that ſhe could not confide the ſecret of her Love unto any other perſon than to her ſelf, that the Princeſs being moved with her reaſons, and ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with her tears, did conſent to give her that mark of complaiſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. But it was on condition that ſhe ſhould not pull up her Vail, and of paſſing for one of <hi>Balabai</hi>'s Servants. <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd into the Gallery to contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate, as he uſed to do, <hi>Balabai</hi> did preſently repair thither alſo; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied by <hi>Alzira,</hi> who having caſt her Eyes upon the Prince
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:150170:22"/>through her Vail, which was of a very thin Stuff, did preſently know him for her Deliverer, with whom her imagination was continually prepoſſeſſed. Such an unexpected rencounter, did give her ſo much joy, ſuch an emotion of Spirits, and ſo many other different moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on the ſudden, that ſhe ſwooned away. <hi>Balabai</hi> affrighted with ſeeing her in that condition, did carry her to her Chamber, with the aſſiſtance of another Woman. So ſoon as the Princeſs was reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered out of her Swoon, ſhe caſt her Eyes on all ſides, perhaps thinking ſtill to ſee that dear Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject which had cauſed ſo ſudden a change in her: But ſhe perceiving no body but <hi>Balabai,</hi> who was weeping on her Beds ſide, <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zira,</hi> recalling to mind that paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which her favorite had for <hi>Ali Hamet,</hi> and thinking withal, that the Prince was the ſame Perſon who had ſaved her life, or at leaſt
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:150170:22"/>was ſo much like him, as to awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in her Heart all the ſentiments of Love and acknowledgments ſhe had had for that Generous un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Perſon, did no longer look on <hi>Balabai</hi> but as her Rival, from whom it was requiſite that ſhe ſhould conceal her ſecret for the future; and to that purpoſe ſhe did perſwade her, that her Swoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was an effect of the averſion which ſhe had for that Prince, and of the diſturbance which ſhe had been in at the ſight of her Fathers Enemy. <hi>Balabai,</hi> who truſted to her Words, durſt no longer pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe unto her the Office of Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter. But <hi>Alzira,</hi> who had an extream impatiency of ſeeing the Prince again, did feign to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned at her Favorit's misfortune, and did promiſe to overcome for her ſake all the Antipathy which ſhe had againſt <hi>Ali Hamet,</hi> and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to ſpeak kindly to him. <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lakai</hi> pierc'd throughly with the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:150170:23"/>Princeſſes bounty, did make uſe of that good diſpoſition ſhe was in, and having learn'd that the Prince had continued in the Gallery, ſhe went thither again with <hi>Alzira,</hi> who did no longer mind the hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of her Face, as ſhe had done the firſt time. <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at the loſs of ſo many op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities of learning ſome news of that Perſon which had given him ſo much Love, did begin to fear of never more ſeeing that charming Object, when that he perceived <hi>Balabai</hi> drawing near unto him, accompanied with <hi>Alzi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra,</hi> who comming up, did ſpeak <hi>Portugues</hi> to him. <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> was ſo pleaſingly ſurpriz'd at the ſecond ſight of this Beautiful Perſon, that he remain'd immovable, all his Senſes being ſo imploy'd on her, that her forgot to give her an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. <hi>Balabai</hi> ſeeing him thus ſurpriz'd, did fear that he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood not the <hi>Portugues</hi> Language.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:150170:23"/>But <hi>Alzira</hi> having inquired of him if he had never been at <hi>Feſs</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that <hi>Maucaden</hi> had made him Priſoner; It was no difficult thing for <hi>Maucaden</hi> to make me a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, replied the Prince, ſeeing that another Perſon had already deprived me of my Liberty, and that I ſought after nothing more than the returning into my Chaines. That Anſwer cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſome diſorder in <hi>Alzira,</hi> fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing leaſt he ſhould mean that to <hi>Balabai:</hi> Mean time, the more ſhe examined him, the more did ſhe confirm her ſelf in her paſſion, finding in him all the ſame fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of that Perſon who had made her in Love: But ſhe could not comprehend by what adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that Prince had happened to be at <hi>Feſs</hi> ſo opportunely to ſave her life. She was going to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire that of him, had not <hi>Balabai</hi> interrupted their converſation, to learn from <hi>Alzira</hi> what 'twas he
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:150170:24"/>ſaid. She gave her to underſtand, that the Prince had a moſt ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Heart, and that he was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing concerning the loſs of his Liberty, when ſhe interrupted them. <hi>Balabai</hi> raviſhed with that anſwer, did conjure her to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue the converſation. Then did the Princeſs intreat <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> to inform her how he had come to loſe his Liberty, and who was that Perſon that had depriv'd him of it. The Prince, after a ſigh, told her, that the deſire of acquiring ſome reputation, by rendring him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Maſter of the City of <hi>Feſs,</hi> ingag'd him to examine the Place in a diſguiſe; but that the fates had deſigned it otherwiſe. His Modeſty had hindred him from faying more, had not the Princeſs preſſed him to continue. What can I ſay, that you know not bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than I do my ſelf? continued <hi>Ali Hamet.</hi> A roaring Lyon, that I had the good Fortune to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:150170:24"/>gave me the opportunity of ſaving you, and of loſing my ſelf: For from that very moment that I did ſee you, I lov'd you with the moſt real and the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt paſſion that ever was. Though this diſcourſe was very confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable unto <hi>Alzira</hi>'s ſentiments, ſhe could not forbear bluſhing, and being diſcompos'd at it. <hi>Palabai,</hi> who perceived the diſorder ſhe was in, had the curoſity to learn the cauſe. The Princeſs told her, that <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> had cauſed ſome diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance in her at the recital which he made her of a Combate which he had had on her Fathers Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories. With your favour, inform me, continued the Prince, who it is that I love in you; the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of your condition can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther increaſe nor diminiſh my Love, and I even feel an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward joy, at the thoughts that you are not <hi>Bembuca's</hi> Daughter. Then you would not have lov'd the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:150170:25"/>Princeſs of <hi>Feſs?</hi> replied <hi>Alzira</hi> haſtily. Alas! replied the Prince, Love gave me not time to delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, when I beheld you; and I had ſo little power over my paſſion, that I believe I had lov'd you, though you had been a Chriſtian Slave. The Princeſs raviſh'd that ſhe was belov'd for her meer Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty's ſake, and without any aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance from her birth in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, was preparing to anſwer him ſomething very obliging, when an <hi>Eunuque</hi> came, and told her that the Queen had asked for her. The Prince remain'd very well fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with this converſation, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving well by his Miſtriſles diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, that his paſſion was not diſpleaſing to her. Mean time <hi>Gayland</hi> had ſent to <hi>Feſs</hi> a confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Perſon to treat with <hi>Bem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buca,</hi> in order to <hi>Ali Hamet's</hi> Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty. <hi>Bembuca,</hi> who had other deſignes, did continually propoſe great difficuties to the concluſion
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:150170:25"/>of that Treaty; yet he expreſſed a very great eſteem for <hi>Ali Hamet.</hi> And whether it was to delude the Vulgar, by his ſeeming pretences, or that he deſign'd to amuſe the Prince, that he might have no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt of his Artifices, he had him invited to all the diveriſements of the Court; and did endeavour by all ſorts of means to render his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment leſs weariſome. <hi>Ali Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met</hi> had paſſed two Days with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſeeing of his Miſtriſs, and was fruitleſly buſying of himſelf in find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out an opportunity to ſpeak with her, when that he was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated by the Prince of <hi>Feſs,</hi> to ſee the Combate of a furious Lyon againſt a moſt Savage Bear. Thoſe kind of Spectacles being of very great requeſt amongſt the <hi>Africans,</hi> the Kings of <hi>Feſs</hi> do often uſe ſuch kindes of divertiſments. <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> hoping that there he might behold that Charming Perſon who had made him in Love, did great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:150170:26"/>rejoyce at his going thither. So ſoon as he was entred the place which was deſigned him, he looked on all ſides, and particularly in that place where the Queens Maids of Honour were ſeated, in hopes to find <hi>Alzira</hi> amongſt them, and did begin to be in ſome diſorder at his not ſeeing of her, when at laſt he eſpied her fitting next to the Queen, which very near that place in which he himſelf was. <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zira,</hi> placed thus amongſt the Royal Family, did extreamly ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe the Prince; and though the Splendor of her Beauty did tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the Luſtre of her Jewels, yet the magnificent Apparel in which ſhe was dreſſed, did afford him new Charms. He doubted then no longer, but that ſhe was the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of <hi>Feſs;</hi> but he already Lov'd her with ſo much paſſion, that this new knowledge cauſed no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable alteration in his mind. The Beaſts did fight with an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:150170:26"/>fierceneſs. And while that the Spectators were giving their approbations on this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> had continually his Eyes fixed on the Princeſs, who did not take off hers from behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, but to look down in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, and ſo ſoon as ſhe raiſed them up again, they would meet with the Princes, which did ſpeak in their Language a thouſand ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and paſſionate things to her; all which ſhe eaſily Interpreted, through the great Sympathy which was already between them. The Combate, which had laſted a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable time, was at an end through the death of thoſe fierce Animals. The two Lovers were obliged to ſeparate themſelves ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner than they would have wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Love, who was the only Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of all their thoughts, did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually ſet them on contriving ſome means of ſeeing and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining one another again, with
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:150170:27"/>their Amorous paſſions. <hi>Ali Hamet,</hi> did conſtantly walk in ſuch places of the Palace as he judg'd that the Princeſs might paſs by, where he would build a thouſaind different projects; ſometimes he was for going into the Princeſſes Appart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; a moment after, he would propoſe to himſelf the gaining of ſome <hi>Eunuque</hi> to his Service with ſome Liberalities, who might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver his Letters to <hi>Alzira.</hi> But ſo ſoon as he was going about the executing of either of his projects, he would fall again into his firſt irreſolutions, and finally would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to Love her for ever, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out undertaking any thing that ſhould diſpleaſe her. <hi>Alzira,</hi> mean time, who did continually enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain her ſelf with <hi>Balabai</hi> on the merit and good meen of <hi>Ali Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met,</hi> obſerv'd in their converſations that her Rivals paſſion did increaſe as oft as ſhe beheld her Lover, which made her once reſolve to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:150170:27"/>bring as many obſtacles as ſhe could to their enterview. But by reaſon that <hi>Balabai</hi> was never abſent from her, and that ſhe her ſelf had an extream impatiency to ſee <hi>Ali Hamet,</hi> ſhe changed her mind, and choſe rather to ſee her Lover in the preſence of her Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val, than to deprive her ſelf any longer of that pleaſure. And ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king advantage of <hi>Balabai</hi>'s Idle paſſion, ſhe adviſed her not to ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect thoſe favourable diſpoſitions in which the Prince was for her ſake; giving her to underſtand, the better to deceive her, that ſhe ſhould no longer be ſorry to ſee her eſpouſe the Prince, ſeeing that it might contribute towards the peace betwixt <hi>Bembuca</hi> and <hi>Gay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. Balabai</hi> being perſwaded through the Princeſs's Bounty, did confide her ſecrets unto one of thoſe <hi>Eunuques</hi> that ſerved her, and having engag'd him by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents and promiſes faithfully to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:150170:28"/>ſerve her, ſhe did propoſe to the Princeſs to write to <hi>Ali Hamet,</hi> to give him notice that he ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair at night unto the <hi>Eunuques</hi> Chamber, where they might enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain him at leiſure. <hi>Alzira</hi> over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd that her Rival had thought on this expedient, did write to him a ſhort Note in <hi>Portugues,</hi> to give him notice that he ſhould not in the leaſt ſcruple to follow that <hi>Eunuque,</hi> who would conduct him to a place where he ſhould find ſome Perſons that were very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to learn whether his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation was as agreeable as his meen was advantageous. After that every body was retired, the <hi>Eunuque</hi> did carefully carry that little Note to the Prince, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it with all the joy imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, and deferr'd no longer to follow the <hi>Eunuque,</hi> than what ſerved to read the Note. You may eaſily imagin with what exceſs of joy <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> was tranſported
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:150170:28"/>at his entring into the <hi>Eunuques</hi> Chamber, where the Princeſs and <hi>Balabai</hi> did expect him. They were ſo aſhamed at ſuch an Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that they ſcarce would lift up their Eyes to look on him. <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zira</hi> would have hid her baſhful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs under pretence that this Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was under her Rivals name, and ſhe thought that at the moſt ſhe could but tax her ſelf for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving too much of complaiſance for her Friend. And <hi>Balabai,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing authoriz'd by the Princeſs's preſence, did caſt on her again all thoſe ſecret reproaches which her Modeſty and her Virtue did make her to conceit. In fine, both the one and the other did think their weakneſs very pardonable, when they reflected on the good meen of the Prince. <hi>Alzira</hi> told him in <hi>Portugues,</hi> that the aſſiduous ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſs with which he had look'd on her during the Combate of the Lyon and the Bear did make her
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:150170:29"/>fancy that he had ſomething to ſay to her—You are not decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in that, moſt charming Princeſs, ſaid <hi>Ali Hamet,</hi> interrupting her, I had ſo much joy to be ſatisfied as to your real Condition, finding that you were born of the Noble Blood of the <hi>Cherifs,</hi> that I thought my ſelf oblig'd to you, for that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent fraud which you had uſed, in the concealing of your Rank from me. But you had aſſur'd me, replied <hi>Alzira,</hi> that that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſhould have no conſiderable advantage over your mind, and that it would produce no alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in your Love. I do confeſs to you, reply'd the Prince, that it had been difficult for me to have added any thing unto that ſtrong paſſion which I had already for you. Yet I was ſo ſurpriz'd to ſee that a Perſon of ſo perfect a Beauty, and of ſo high a Birth, did not diſapprove of my Love, that it has enter'd me into new engagements;
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:150170:29"/>and I was reſolv'd to expoſe my ſelf unto all ſorts of perils to ſee you again, when the <hi>Eunuque</hi> brought me the Bill. <hi>Alzira,</hi> who was in ſome kind of Confuſion at thoſe laſt Words, would have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus'd her ſelf from having writ that Note; and having leſs deſigns of pleaſuring her Rival, than of preſerving her Modeſty, ſhe told him, without any further reflexion, that it was to <hi>Balabai,</hi> and not to her ſelf, that he was indebted for that kindneſs. The Prince turning him immediately towards <hi>Balabai,</hi> and taking her by the hand, he kiſſed it with ſome little force, and return'd her thanks for the good Office that ſhe had rendred him. <hi>Balabai</hi> deceived thus by this ſhew of Love that was ſo like to a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and believing that the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs did really ſerve her with good ſucceſs, did after that hearken with a great deal of ſatisfaction to all the tender diſcourſes of the two
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:150170:30"/>Lovers, and did facilitate to them at divers times, the means of fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ſeeing and entertaining one another. <hi>Ali Hamet's</hi> long de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment did ſerve but to make his Merits the better known at the Court of <hi>Feſs,</hi> and to caſt new fears and jealouſies in <hi>Bembu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca</hi>'s mind, who did not doubt but that a Prince that had ſuch ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar qualities would one Day ſet up the intereſt which he pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Crown of <hi>Feſs.</hi> Thoſe reaſons, with that hatred he had for <hi>Gayland,</hi> did reſolve him on <hi>Ali Hamet</hi>'s ruine. He ſought di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ways to accompliſh it, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt diſtruſt by any body, fearing leaſt he ſhould draw on himſelf the hatred of his People, in ſpilling the Blood of <hi>Mahomet.</hi> After divers conſiderations on this Buſineſs, it came in his mind, that <hi>Talbor</hi> had done wounderful things with Gun-powder, which made him of opinion that he might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:150170:30"/>ſuch a Mine as ſhould make no great noiſe in the blowing up under the Princes Chamber, and yet cruſh him to Death under the ruines of that building, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any diſtruſt that it had been deſign'd, ſeeing that the uſe of Gun-powder was yet ſcarce known at <hi>Feſs.</hi> He propoſed his deſign to <hi>Talbor,</hi> who not knowing that it was intended againſt the Prince, did promiſe the King to make a Mine that ſhould act in the ſame manner that he deſir'd, and with little or no noiſe. He went about it very ſecretly, and when it was ready to ſpring, he gave the King notice, who was overjoy'd at it. The Eve to that Execution Day, <hi>Bembuca</hi> being only with the Prince of <hi>Feſs,</hi> and the Princeſs <hi>Alzira</hi> his Children, he advertiſed them of his deſign, that they might not be ſurpriz'd with the noiſe that they ſhould hear; and to ſet forth that important piece of Service,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:150170:31"/>which he deſign'd to render them by <hi>Ali Hamets</hi> death, he ſpoke to them in theſe terms.</p>
            <p>Our Bleſſed Prophet, the moſt intimate Friend to our Great <hi>Alla,</hi> has always been favourable to me: For after that he had deſtroyed the <hi>Almanzors,</hi> and the <hi>Beneme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rignis,</hi> he was pleas'd to place me on the Throne, preferably unto the Father of <hi>Ali Hamet,</hi> and of divers others of our Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, which the Right of Blood did call unto it before me. He has given me the Victory over mine Enemies, and he has come in his own Perſon to defend my dear Daughter from the fury of the Lyon. But he did never give me a more ſenſible token of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, than in cauſing <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> to fall into my Hands, through the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of my Friend <hi>Gayland,</hi> who is the onely Perſon that might one Day diſturb my quiet, and hinder you my Children from ſucceeding me in
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:150170:31"/>the Throne. All theſe reaſons, my dear Children, have made me re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve the deſtruction of that Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. <hi>Talbor</hi> the Stranger, has by my order contriv'd a Mine under his Appartment, this Night you will hear it fall, be not concern'd at it, and before the People feign to lament the fate of that unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Prince.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alzira,</hi> ſtruck through the Heart at the news of this cruel reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, was in the greateſt trouble imaginable to conſtrain her ſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her Father: Yet ſhe did repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to him, that the Great <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met</hi> might be offended at ſuch an Action, and that it were much better to leave to that Prophet the care of his own Revenge, than to undertake it himſelf. But <hi>Bem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buca</hi> not regarding her reaſons, made anſwer, that <hi>Mahomet</hi> had ſufficiently given him to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand his Will in that, by <hi>Ali Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mets</hi> Impriſonment. The Princeſs
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:150170:32"/>daring not to reply any further, thought of nothing more but of concealing that diſorder ſhe was in. The King, after he had enjoyn'd them ſilence, did retire, and <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zira</hi> return'd into her Appartment overcome with grief and ſorrow. But yet ſhee took <hi>Ali Hamet's</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts in hand, without abando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of her ſelf unto a fruitleſs deſpair, and did reſolve to hazard all, for the ſafety of her Lover; wherefore under ſome other pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, ſhe cauſed an <hi>Eunuques</hi> dreſs to be brought to her, and having ſubtilly rid her ſelf of thoſe Perſons that were about her, ſhe changed her habit, and went into <hi>Ali Haemet's</hi> Appartment. The Prince, who preſently knew her face, was very much ſurpriz'd at this diſguiſe: The Princeſs, who did bluſh to ſee her ſelf in that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, did intreat him to ſuſpend all the Judgments that an Action ſeemingly ſo raſh might oblige
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:150170:32"/>him to make of her. I confeſs, <hi>continued ſhe,</hi> that I have not had leiſure, to make reflexions, a too preſſing intereſt has made me act, and I have not wav'd to expoſe my ſelfe to Ruine, when your Life was concern'd. The Prince greatly mov'd at his Miſtriſſes bounties, caſt himſelf at her feet, and would have ſpoken tender and paſſionate things to her, as he us'd to do. But, Loſe no time, reply'd <hi>Alzira,</hi> interrupting him, my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther has reſolv'd your ruine, and by Morning this great Appart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will be but Rubbiſh, under which you are to periſh; you muſt inſtantly retire, and return into your Territories, where I flatter my ſelf, that for Love of me, you will endeavour a Peace, and that you will not fail to ſend me of your news ſo ſoon as arriv'd. She with that gave him a Pidgeon, which ſhe had carefully brought up, and aſſur'd him that if he ſed
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:150170:33"/>it with a certain Seed which ſhe named, it would be eaſie for them frequently to Write to one another; becauſe that that kind of Pidgeon did never fail of returning into thoſe places where they have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready been fed; which thing is ſo well known, that they are made uſe of as ſwift Poſts in divers places of <hi>Africa. Ali Hamet,</hi> ſcarce minding the danger that he was threatned with, had much to do to reſolve to depart, and to diſtance himſelf from his Princeſs. But <hi>Alzira</hi> did ſo earneſtly preſs him to think on his ſafety for her ſake, ſeeing that he neglected it on his own account, that at laſt he went out, followed by the diſguiſed <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zira,</hi> who had already taken all the neceſſary meaſures to prevent all obſtacles. She did accompany him unto the laſt Gate of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, and having not the power to take leave of him, ſhe ſuddenly ſtole from his ſight, taking the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:150170:33"/>way to her Appartment, very much afflicted at the Princes departure, though well ſatisfied that ſhe had ſaved her Lovers life. She was ſcarce got into her Chamber, when that the Mine was ſprung, with that ſucceſs that <hi>Talbor</hi> had promiſed. All the Palace was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm'd at it, the Princeſſes Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men came about her in a great diſorder, and at every moment there came into her Chamber ſome <hi>Eunuque</hi> which brought her ſome new circumſtance of that extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary event. The confuſion was ſo great, that it was long before the truth of what had paſſed was known. At laſt the Princeſs was aſſur'd that <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> was the only conſiderable Perſon that had periſhed under the Ruines of that Fabriek. There were ſome alſo that poſitively ſaid they had ſeen his Body ſhatter'd in a thouſand pieces. Though <hi>Alzira</hi> had been prepared againſt all thoſe diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:150170:34"/>ſhe was much concerned, fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring leſt that peradventure the Prince might have returned into his appartment. But thoſe diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bances of mind were over, when the King ſent her word of the misfortune that had happened, and of the fruitleſs pains that had been already taken to unbury the Body of <hi>Ali Hamet,</hi> which had not yet been found. <hi>Balabai</hi> came in that inſtant to the Princeſs, and in her preſence did yield unto all the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects that ſo great a ſorrow could inſpire into a moſt afflicted Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. <hi>Alzira</hi> did endeavour to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort her, and leſt that thoſe diſorders that ſhe was in ſhould be conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her diſadvantage, ſhe diſcreetly gave out, that a Maid Servant whom <hi>Balabai</hi> had lov'd very well had periſhed under the Ruines of that Appartment, in which ſhe lay. Mean time <hi>Bembuca,</hi> who applau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded himſelf for the happy ſucceſs of his deſign, and who made uſe
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:150170:34"/>of all the cautiouſneſs imaginable to prevent that he ſhould ever be ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected of having any Hand in <hi>Ali Hamets</hi> misfortune, who he thought certainly dead, gave out orders to have <hi>Talbor</hi> convy'd to the next Sea-Port, that he might be ſent back to <hi>Tangire,</hi> which belongs to the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> Thus every one in <hi>Feſs</hi> did believe that this great accident had happened through the fault of thoſe Architects that had had the ordering of that building. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter divers fruitleſs cares to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh the Body of <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> from others, the King perceiving that all thoſe that were found involved in the Ruines were ſo ſhatter'd that it was impoſſible ſcarce to know one, he, to impoſe the more on the People, order'd that a Body, which he pretended to be that of <hi>Ali Hamet,</hi> ſhould be Imbalmed; after which he had all things got in a readineſs for the celebration of his
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:150170:35"/>Funeral Rites after the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as they us'd to be rendred un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Princes of the Blood of the <hi>Cherifs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alzira</hi> ſympathiſing with <hi>Balabai</hi> in her afflictions, did not omit any thing that might give her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. She was even on the point of letting her know that the Prince was not dead; but well foreſeeing that the Joy of a Rival would cauſe her more trouble than would the ſorrow of a Friend, the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of her affections did always diſwade her from giving ſo much ſatisfaction to that afflicted Lover. Alas! would <hi>Balabai</hi> ſay, you love but a meer Chimera, whoſe ſingle remembrance affords you both Joy and Delight; judge by that of the ſorrow which I do feel in the loſs of a Prince ſo accompliſhed as was the Young <hi>Cherif,</hi> who had infus'd a paſſion in me from the very firſt time that I had ſeen him, and who already
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:150170:35"/>had ſuch advantageous thoughts of me, as you are ſenſible of. The Princeſs not anſwering poſitively unto her diſcourſes, was endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to comfort her, when that the King ſent her Word, that at laſt the Body of the unfortunate <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> had been taken up, and that it was requiſite that ſhe ſhould prepare her ſelf to aſſiſt the the next Day at thoſe magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Funerals which he had orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſhould be performed for him. The name of <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new all <hi>Balabai's</hi> ſorrows, and <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zira</hi> was no longer in a conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to aſſiſt her; ſhe was ſo trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled her ſelf with hearing this cruel news, that ſhe remain'd without ſenſeor motion, not being able to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that it was true, neither having the power of ſatisfying her ſelf on a thing which ſhe ſo feared; and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending alſo leſt that her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourite ſhould take notice of the concern which ſhe took in the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:150170:36"/>Prince's intereſt. <hi>Balabai</hi> ſhed tears, while that <hi>Alzira</hi> was making a thouſand reflections: Now ſhe fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that the Prince might have returned into his Chamber, a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment after ſhe would pleaſe her ſelf with the thoughts of his departure, remembring that ſhe had accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied him unto the fartheſt Gate of the Palace, neither could ſhe ſee any likely hood, that that Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy which was talked of could be his. Yet all her reaſon could not ſettle her allarm'd Love, ſhe was oblig'd to give out, that ſhe was Sick, taking to her Bed, under that pretence to conceal from every Body the diſorders that ſhe was in. The King, who did moſt tenderly Love his Daughter, was extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly afflicted at her Sickneſs, and did not appear at <hi>Ali Hamet's</hi> Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals as he had deſign'd: He would go every moment to the Princeſs, and ſo ſoon as he was returned from thence, he would
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:150170:36"/>ſend thither the Prince his Son. The Prince having one Day ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd, that <hi>Balabai</hi> was weeping by the Princeſs, he was mov'd with a tender compaſſion at the tears of ſo Beautiful a Perſon, and endeavouring to conſolate her, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion draw tears from him alſo, which cauſed an effect ſomewhat extraordinary. For <hi>Balabai</hi> being ſurpriſed with ſeeing the Prince to weep, was willing to make <hi>Alzira</hi> obſerve her Brothers good Nature; but the Prince interrupted her, and aſſur'd her, that his Siſter had no ſhare in thoſe tears, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion had forc'd from him at the ſight of the ſorrow of ſo Beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful a Perſon as ſhe her ſelf was. That anſwer cauſed <hi>Balabai</hi> to bluſh, not expecting it; and how great ſoever her ſorrow was, ſhe was ſomewhat moved with that flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, which made her return the Prince thanks for his Bounty. <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zira,</hi> who maugre all her diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:150170:37"/>of Mind, did ſtill flatter her ſelf with the hopes that her Lover was not dead, was not diſpleaſed that the Prince her Brother had ſpoken ſo obligingly to her Favorite, and did reſolve to advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage her ſelf by that good diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in making <hi>Balabai</hi> wholly to forget <hi>Ali Hamet.</hi> So that at all times that her ſorrows did give her ſome intervals, ſhe would not loſe any occaſion to mention the Beauty of <hi>Balabai</hi> to her Brother, and of entertaining her with the great advantages that a Perſon who ſhould have the good For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune to pleaſe the Prince, might expect. The Prince would heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to her with pleaſure, and <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labai</hi> would confeſs, that if after the loſs which ſhe had ſo lately had, ſhe could be capable of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mov'd with any thing, the Prince ſhould not be indifferent to her. <hi>Alzira,</hi> who would not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear till ſhe had received news
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:150170:37"/>from her Love, did paſs many Days without ſtirring forth of her Chamber; which gave means to the Prince, who did hourly viſit her, frequently to entertain <hi>Balabai.</hi> He found her much to his mind, and thoſe enterviews did greatly increaſe that eſteem which he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready had for her. There being no great diſtance between that kind Sentiment, and Love, the Prince ſtay'd not long before he paſſionately lov'd her. <hi>Balabai,</hi> who had at the firſt hearkened un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Prince but through a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playſancy to <hi>Alzira,</hi> had much to do to ſuffer him to ſpeak of Love; ſhe had reſolv'd never to love any thing more after the unhappy ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of her firſt Amours; the thoughts of her dead Lover, did contribute to confirm her in that reſolution, being prepoſſeſed, that only <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> was worthy of being beloved.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:150170:38"/>
While that the Prince of <hi>Feſs</hi> was endeavouring to make her al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her mind, the Court of <hi>Suſs</hi> was in the extreameſt affliction imaginable. The Prince <hi>Gayland</hi> had received news from all parts, of the death of his Kinſman <hi>Ali Hamet;</hi> the certain knowledge which he had of <hi>Bembuca</hi>'s wicked Nature, did make him think that <hi>Ali Hamet's</hi> death had been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd, which obliged him to a War, and to exhort all his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to do their utmoſt, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge ſuch a perfidious Action. The Young <hi>Cherif</hi> being highly regretted, every one did put him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in a poſture of revenging his death, and <hi>Gayland</hi> had ſoon found himſelf at the head of a numerous Army, had not <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> return'd, which did moſt pleaſingly ſurpriſe the Court. His Uncle gave him a thouſand marks of his affection and tenderneſs. There was no other talk but of divertiſements,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:150170:38"/>and every one did ſet forwards in expreſſing the joy which they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the Princes Arrival. <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> bearing in mind how that his Miſtriſs had recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him, the diſpoſing of things towards a Peace, did highly praiſe to his Uncle all the good Offices which he had received from <hi>Bem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buca,</hi> and did perſwade him, the better to ſerve his Princeſs, that <hi>Bembuca</hi> not being able to reſiſt the inſtances of his Council, who did continually inſpire him to rid his Hand of ſo dangerous an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, he had the Generoſity to give him notice of it, and deceiving all the Miniſters of State, in ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conveying him out of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace unknown to all. <hi>Gayland,</hi> who could not know <hi>Bembuca</hi> by all thoſe Actions of Generoſity, was in a ſtrange ſurpriſal at the Princes recital, and not being able to comprehend how that the King of <hi>Feſs</hi> ſhould be ſo ſtrangely chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:150170:39"/>he judg'd that nothing but <hi>Ali Hamet's</hi> merit could work ſo great a Miracle.</p>
            <p>The Prince having thus diſpoſed his Uncles mind to Peace, thought of nothing more but of giving his Princeſs ſome news of himſelf. He had with great care preſerved that Pidgeon which ſhe had given him, and having obſerv'd all that ſhe had preſcribed him as to the feeding of it, to oblige his return, he let him go, after he had faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to his Feet this following Letter.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>ALLA, <hi>and his Great Prophet, have conducted me to</hi> Suſs, <hi>where I have found my <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring himſelf to revenge my death; the noiſe of which had already reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo far. My return has cauſed an univerſal joy, I am the only Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that cannot rejoyce, when I think that I am at an hundred Leagues diſtance from that which I
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:150170:39"/>love. Why would you not let me die when you could not ſave me with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſending me from you? I am ſo well taught to deſpiſe death, that it cannot ſtartle me at any time: But to live without you, that only thought is more horrid to me, than all the moſt Cruel deaths. Judge of the Power which you have over me, ſeeing that notwithſtanding all the reaſons which I have to have</hi> Bem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buca, <hi>I have told my Uncle, that I owe him a thouſand Obligations, that he had frequently oppoſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf againſt his Miniſters of State who did adviſe him to deſtroy me, and that, finally, not being able to defend himſelf any longer from gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them his conſent, he cauſed me to be conveyed ſecretly out of the Palace, and after that, had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived his whole Court in publiſhing that I was dead. I hope that a Peace will be in a ſhort time conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Mean time ſend me ſome news from you, and be perſwaded
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:150170:40"/>that it is the only joy that I can receive in the condition that I find my ſelf at preſent</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Pidgeon being arrived in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Princeſſes Cloſet, ſhe read her Lovers Letter with all the pleaſure imaginable; her joy was ſo viſible on her Face, that it had been impoſſible for her to have conceal'd it. The Prince and <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labai</hi> having afterwards taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of it, ſhe told them that her joy did proceed from that her Sickneſs had given an occaſion to a good intelligence between two Perſons which were very dear unto her: For <hi>Balabai,</hi> who was of the humour of moſt part of Women, had at laſt accuſtomed her ſelf unto the Princes paſſionate diſcourſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es. The two Lovers thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves oblig'd unto her for her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſancy, and if at any time ſhe retired her ſelf in private, to read over again that Letter which <hi>Ali
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:150170:40"/>Hamet</hi> had ſent her, they judg'd that ſhe did it expreſly to favour their Amours. Mean time ſhe had an extream care of her Pidge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which ſhe ſent back a little while after, with the following An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, having firſt left him a whole Day without Food.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>YOU have reſtor'd me to life againe, in informing me that yours was in ſafety. For, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the aſſurance which I had of your going out of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, I was ſo troubled to hear ſo many different circumſtances of your death, that my allarm'd heart did begin to fear leſt I had been decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, when that I thought you gone. I have a thouſand times revolv'd in my mind all that did paſs at that cruel departure, and a thouſand times I have doubted if I did not deceive my ſelf. I was ſo tired with all the ridiculous ſtories which were made on your death, that I have
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:150170:41"/>been on the very point of undecei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving all the World; having almoſt leſs repugnancy againſt the diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of my love, than at the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that you were no more. I am oblig'd to you for that noble deceit that you have put upon your Uncle. I hope that the King will be mov'd at ſo generous a proceeding, and that at laſt he will open his Eyes to do juſtice to your merits, or rather that he will a ſecond time give his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her Life, in uniting me to you.</hi> Alla <hi>grant it; and let his intimate Friend, our Great Prophet, Crown you with proſperity, and preſerve you for your</hi> Alzira.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <trailer>The End of the firſt Part.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:150170:41"/>
            <head>THE PRINCESS OF FESS.</head>
            <head type="sub">PART II.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>GAYLAND,</hi> who had obſerv'd that his Kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſince his return was much more Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy than uſual, did in vain endeavour to gueſs at the cauſe thereof. <hi>Bembuca's</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity he did very much diſtruſt, and though he was but too cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:150170:42"/>of the Princes virtue, to fear any private intelligence between him and the King of <hi>Feſs,</hi> all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did cauſe ſome diſturbances in his Mind. He was one Day walking with his Nephew on a Tarras, with a deſign cunningly to pierce into the reaſons of his ſadneſs, when that <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> did perceive the Pidgeon which was bringing to him <hi>Alzira's</hi> anſwer. A joy did ſo ſurpriſe him, that without think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he was with his Sovereign, he abrubtly left him, and went up into his appartment, to learn ſome news of his Miſtreſs. This odd kind of proceeding raiſed new doubts in <hi>Gayland,</hi> who had very well obſerv'd that that Pidgeons arrival had cauſed ſome diſorder in his Nephew. And whereas it is a very ordinary thing in that Country to make uſe of Pidgeons to ſend Letters by; he no longer doubted but that <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> had received ſome Letters from <hi>Bem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buca.</hi>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:150170:42"/>All thoſe things that had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded did confirm him in his doubts, which made him reſolve to inform himſelf at what rate ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever. The <hi>African</hi> Princes for the moſt part, are very curious in Falconry. <hi>Gayland,</hi> who had all kind of Falcons, made choice of a caſt of the beſt Hawks, he order'd that they ſhould not be fed of one whole Day, and the next Day he had them kept by two Falconers on the avenues of <hi>Ali Hamet's</hi> Appartment, with order to let them fly, ſo ſoon as they ſhould ſee a Pidgeon go from thence. The Prince failed not the next Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to write a very tender Letter to his Princeſs, which he intruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to his faithful Meſſenger. The Falcons having perceived it ſetting forth, did preſently follow that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Courier, and being preſſed with hunger, they devoured him in an inſtant. The Men took up the Letter, and carryed it to <hi>Gay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:150170:43"/>who found it to be a moſt paſſionate writing: He gueſt by thoſe terms in which it was penn'd, that the Prince was belov'd by <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zira,</hi> and compatiſing in his Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phews love, he was ſorry for what he had done, and did no longer doubt, but that the Princeſs had obtain'd from her Father, both the Life and the Liberty of her Lover. <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> being extreamly dear unto him, and beſides he being weary with making War, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to contribute towards that Marriage, and to ſurpriſe his Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew, in informing him of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution. The ſame Day he call'd him in private, and after that he had expreſſed much kindneſs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him, he told him, that he had a deſign to marry him, and that he would no longer expoſe him unto the perillous hazard of Wars, till he had given him ſome Succeſſors. <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> not doubting but that his Uncle had
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:150170:43"/>caſt his Eyes on ſome of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects in order to his Marriage, was ſo affrighted at that propoſition, that he remain'd ſpeechleſs. <hi>Gay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> did preſs him to ſpeak, and to declare his mind to him without conſtraint. The Prince grown more bold, did aſſure him, that Glory only was his whole ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, further ſaying, that it would be ſhameful for him to Marry before he had wiped off the ſhame of his Priſon by ſome ſignal action. I had reſolv'd, reply'd <hi>Gayland,</hi> to ſend ſome magnificent preſents un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the King of <hi>Feſs,</hi> to return him thanks for having ſet you at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and I was in a mind at the ſame time to have the Princeſs his Daughter ask'd in Marriage for you, but ſince I ſee that you have ſome averſion againſt it—The Princeſs <hi>Alzira,</hi> Sir! reply'd <hi>Ali Hamet,</hi> ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſingly. Yes, <hi>Bembuca's</hi> Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, continued <hi>Gayland;</hi> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that I will not compel you
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:150170:44"/>to any thing, I will not think any longer on it: Ah! my Lord, reply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Ali Hamet,</hi> are not you my So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign? and are you to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult my Will in any thing that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the good of your People? It is not with you, reply'd <hi>Gayland,</hi> that I will make uſe of my Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign rights; and ſeeing that it is Glory only which takes up all your ambition, I will permit you to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that noble deſign. Saying of this, he retir'd, and gave not time to the Prince to anſwer him. Yet he omitted not ſending an Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſador ſecretly, loaden with coſtly preſents, with order to preſent them to <hi>Bembuca,</hi> and to demand <hi>Alzi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> of him, for <hi>Ali Hamet,</hi> who mean time was under moſt cruel perplexities, for having loſt ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable an occaſion of engaging his Uncle to concern himſelf in his Marriage. Sometimes he was for an entire declaration of his Love, a moment after, he would
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:150170:44"/>alter hir mind, fearing leſt that <hi>Gayland</hi> ſhould ill reſent his deſigns on the Princeſs of <hi>Feſs,</hi> without his conſent. While that he was in thoſe agitations, <hi>Alzira</hi> was la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring with an extream applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to render happy her Brother and <hi>Balabai,</hi> who did moſt paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately love one another: ſhe had already ſpoken to the King, in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of thoſe two Lovers, foreſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that one Day ſhe might ſtand in need of a like complaiſance from them; or peradventure that ſhe did take that care to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence <hi>Balabai</hi> in ſome meaſure for the loſs of <hi>Ali Hamet.</hi> It being cuſtomary for the <hi>African</hi> Princes to Eſpouſe thoſe of their own Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects that they beſt like, <hi>Bembuca</hi> made no oppoſition unto the two Lovers happineſs, conſidering that this Marriage would preſerve an union in his Family. <hi>Balabai's</hi> Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, who were very conſiderable at the Court of <hi>Feſs,</hi> did not omit any
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:150170:45"/>thing in which they might expreſs their joy, in publick rejoycing; and the Prince, who was very ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant, having wiſhed that there might be ſome Tilting, cauſed it to be publiſhed throughout all the Cities of the Kingdom of <hi>Feſs</hi> and <hi>Morocco.</hi> All things were getting in readineſs againſt thoſe great Feſtivals, when that <hi>Gayland</hi>'s Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador arriv'd there. <hi>Bembuca,</hi> who was the moſt ſubtle of all Men, was extreamly ſurpriz'd at the Magnificent preſents, and much more at the Embaſſadors demands, being fully perſwaded, that <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> was dead; which made him think that <hi>Gayland,</hi> who had no Succeſſor, did peradventure fear ſome revolt in his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and that he deſign'd to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe on his People, under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of this marriage, in conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from them the Death of his Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew. Thoſe reflexions did oblige him to anſwer this piece of craft
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:150170:45"/>by another, and to ſay to the Embaſſador, that with joy he did yield the Princeſs unto his Maſters Nephew; but whereas it was the belief of the whole Court that <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> was not living, it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that that Prince ſhould ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in Perſon in the City <hi>Feſs,</hi> to undeceive the World, leſt that otherwiſe his Council and People ſhould oppoſe themſelves unto that imaginary Marriage. <hi>Bembuca</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving given this Anſwer, was impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient to inform his Children there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and more particularly <hi>Alzira,</hi> who had ſo great an intereſt in the buſineſs. The Princeſs, being ſurpriz'd with her Fathers diſcourſe, did perceive that her Lover had act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed according to her intentions, and being deſirous to anticipate the Kings deſigns, ſhe told him, with an affected modeſty, that ſhe knew her duty, and that ſhe ſhould obey him without repugnancy. It will not be hard for you to do ſo on
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:150170:46"/>this occaſion, reply'd the King, ſince that we all know that <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> is dead. But what if he ſhould come, Sir, reply'd the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs? would you keep your word? That cannot be, reply'd the King; but ſhould he return, I ſhould aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure my ſelf better of his death, in cauſing him to periſh before my Eyes. <hi>Alzira,</hi> affrighted at thoſe laſt Words, What, Sir, ſaid ſhe, with tears in her Eyes, you would then make me be the pretence un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which you would make an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate Prince of the race of the <hi>Cherifs</hi> to periſh? May the great <hi>Alla</hi> make me die firſt. In ending theſe Words, ſhe caſt her ſelf at his Feet, and did proteſt, that ſhe would not riſe again, till he had firſt promiſed her that he would offer no wrong unto <hi>Ali Hamet,</hi> if he ſhould chance to return, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that it was not impoſſible but that the Prophet <hi>Mahomet</hi> might have wrought a Miracle to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:150170:46"/>a Prince of his own Blood. <hi>Bembuca</hi> admiring his Daughters Credulity, cauſed her to riſe, and granted her requeſt, being prepoſſeſt with this Princes death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gayland's</hi> Embaſſador, who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the cuſtom of the Country, had taken along with him divers Pidgeons, wherewith to give notice to his Prince of the good ſucceſs of his Negotiation, gave him an account of <hi>Bembuca's</hi> Anſwer, and advertiſed him alſo of the Princeſs of <hi>Feſs</hi> his Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, and of the famous Tilting which was preparing to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. So ſoon as <hi>Gayland</hi> did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that Letter he paſſed into <hi>Ali Hamet's</hi> Appartment, and after that he had told him that he had newly rereived Letters from <hi>Feſs,</hi> he told him that <hi>Bembuca</hi> had Marryed both his Children, that there were great Feſtivals prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring for the Marriage of the Prince with <hi>Balabai,</hi> which was already
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:150170:47"/>conſummated, and would ſuddainly be follow'd with that of <hi>Alzira</hi> with another Prince, unto whom her Father has promiſed her. How! my Lord, interrupted <hi>Ali Hamet,</hi> news are ſent you that <hi>Bembuca</hi> is Marrying of the Princeſs <hi>Alzira?</hi> Her Father has already paſſed his Word for it, reply'd <hi>Gayland,</hi> (giving his Embaſſadors Letters;) you will be better informed of this by this Letter which you may read, while I am going to diſpatch a buſineſs of conſequence. The Prince re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main'd ſo aſtoniſted at this cruel news, that he had ſcarce ſo much ſtrength left him as would ſerve to open the Letter which his Uncle had given him. In an inſtant a thouſand violent and paſſionate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns came in his head, having no other thoughts but of ſacrificing that happy Rival unto his Love. That hatred which he already felt againſt him, did ſet him in an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient deſire to read the Letter, to
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:150170:47"/>learn his name. Never was there a ſurpriſe like unto that of <hi>Ali Hamet,</hi> when reading the Letter, he found the great Obligations which he had to his Uncle; he read over the Letter divers times, not eaſily believing a good Fortune ſo little expected, and though he knew very well that <hi>Bembuca</hi> did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to draw him to the Court of <hi>Feſs,</hi> to rid himſelf of him by ſome new artifice, he took ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in thinking that in ſome ſhort time he ſhould be permitted to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold again his moſt dear Princeſs with the Kings conſent, and that of his Uncle, that he did caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide all thoſe other conſiderations that might give him any diſtruſt of <hi>Bembuca's</hi> deſigns. <hi>Gayland,</hi> who had purpoſely abſented himſelf to let him reliſh at eaſe all that joy which he judged that thoſe happy news would afford him, did return into <hi>Ali Hamet's</hi> Chamber, who preſently went to embrace his
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:150170:48"/>Knees ſo ſoon as he did ſee him appear, expreſſing in his actions, and by the diſorder of his diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, how ſenſible he was of this new Obligation. He confeſs'd to him, that he was ſure of <hi>Alzira's</hi> heart, and then humbly intreated him that he would be pleas'd to give him leave to depart with all diligence, that he might be at the Tilting that was preparing at <hi>Feſs,</hi> to have the ſatisfaction of brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a Lance or two there, in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of his dear Princeſs. <hi>Gay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> gave his conſent, and the time preſſing, the next Day he ſent back the ſame Pidgeon which was come from <hi>Feſs,</hi> with a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which he writ to his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour, to order him him to get in readineſs, as ſecretly as he could poſſible, all ſuch things as the Prince ſhould ſtand in need of for the Tilting. Though that the Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadour did think it impoſſible for the Prince to come in time for
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:150170:48"/>the Tilting, yet he performed ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly his Commiſſion. Mean time <hi>Ali Hamet,</hi> unto whom love did facilitate all things, made ſuch di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, that he render'd himſelf at <hi>Feſs</hi> before the Tilting was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. He haſtily did Arm himſelf, and being mounted on an <hi>Arabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Horſe, he preſented himſelf at the Bariers at the ſame time that the Prince of <hi>Feſs,</hi> who was very dexterious at thoſe kind of exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, had already overcome divers brave Cavaliers, and was going to receive the Priſe from his far <hi>Balabai's</hi> hands; only <hi>Mauca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> who might have diſputed it with him, declining the running againſt him. This Prince, ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of his Conqueſts, was demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a haughty accent whether there was any perſon more that would be born down, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeated, when that <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> made ſign with his hand to give him notice that he would brake a
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:150170:49"/>Lance with him. The Prince of <hi>Feſs,</hi> being impatient to puniſh that preſumptuous Perſon, did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſet himſelf in a readineſs to give him ſatisfaction. The Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page of the unknown Perſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very magnificent, did oblige all Perſons, and eſpecially the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, to caſt their Eyes on him. He was ſo well on Horſe, and he did handle his Lance with ſo good a Grace, that it was preſently judg'd that he might give the Prince ſome work. Yet were not the opinions divided, and after thoſe proofs that the Prince had already given of his valour, and dexterity, no body did doubt but that he would gain the advantage likewiſe over the ſtranger. The ſignal being given, they both ſet forth with ſuch a ſwiftneſs as did ſhew the impatiency which they both had to joyn one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. At this firſt encounter they diſorder'd each other with almoſt
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:150170:49"/>an equal advantage, which did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe that good opinion that every one had already for the Stranger. The Prince of <hi>Feſs</hi> being fretted at the reſiſtance that his concurrent had made, did not ſtay long without ſetting forth the ſecond time. <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> went off alſo, and did juſtle the Prince of <hi>Feſs</hi> with ſo much ſtrength, that having cauſed him to quit his ſtirrups, he bore him down. The Princes fall did alarm all the Spectators. The Ladies were already making of imprecations againſt this Stranger, when that the Prince blaming of their injuſtice, let them know that he had received no hurt; and he himſelf did there admire the ſtrength and dexterity of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror. The brave <hi>Maucaden,</hi> who through reſpect had wav'd run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning againſt the Prince of <hi>Feſs,</hi> did intreat the King that he might have leave to revenge him, thinking that after he had over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:150170:50"/>two Cavaliers of <hi>Morcco,</hi> who had the reputation of being the moſt valiant of all <hi>Africa,</hi> that this Stranger would have much to do to reſiſt him. The great attention with which the Ladies did look on <hi>Ali Hamet,</hi> made them to take notice of his Shield, on which there was pictu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a Cavalier that was overco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of a Lyon with one hand, and was holding forth his other hand to a Lady, with certain <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bick</hi> Words, which ſignified, <hi>In ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving her, I my own ſelf have loſt.</hi> No body did comprehend the ſenſe of thoſe Words. <hi>Alzira,</hi> who did find them very confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable unto her Lovers adventure, did obſerve him more carefully than ſhe had done before; and the more that ſhe examined him, the more did ſhe find his port, ſhape, and good meen to be like <hi>Ali Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met's.</hi> Then this unknown Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Valour did the more confirm
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:150170:50"/>him in her thoughts: But when ſhe did reflect on <hi>Ali Hamet's</hi> hundred Leagues diſtance from thence, and that the Juſting had been but very lately publiſhed, ſhe did fear that her love did deceive her, ſeeing it was impoſſible that her Lover could be advertis'd of that Feſtival and got thither in ſo ſhort a time. While that the Princeſs was in thoſe agitations of Spirit, the brave Stranger did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe that admiration which was already had for him, by the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage which he had over <hi>Mauca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den. Balabai,</hi> who was to give the Priſe appointed for the Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, did intreat the King to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence her from that ceremony, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing ſome repugnancy againſt recompencing of that Perſon who had deprived the Prince and her Brother of the Victory. The King unwilling to conſtrain her, did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point the Princeſs <hi>Alzira</hi> for the preſenting of the Priſe to the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:150170:51"/>Victor, who was already alighted, and was drawn near to the Kings Scaffold; every body had an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream deſire to know him, and he was earneſtly preſſed to pull off his head piece, as is the cuſtom; but the ſtranger did ſtill put it off, till being call'd by the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs to receive the Priſe which he had ſo well merited, ſhe requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him to diſcover his Face. <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> had not the power to refuſe his Miſtris: He preſented himſelf bare headed to her, and did receive from her fair hands a Cimiter ſtudded with precious Stones. It is eaſie to imagine how much the ſight of a Perſon that was thought dead, did ſurpriſe the whole Court. <hi>Balabai</hi> remembring a Face which had been ſo agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to her, was ſo ſurprz'd at it, that ſhe fell into a ſwoon after ſhe had given a great ſhriek. <hi>Alzira,</hi> who notwithſtanding all the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonings which ſhe had framed
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:150170:51"/>within her ſelf, did ſtill retain a ſecret foreknowledge that this brave Stranger could be none other than <hi>Ali Hamet,</hi> was agitated with a thouſand confuſed notions, joy fear, love, did all at once move in her Soul, but the ſurprize that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one was in, did cauſe that the leſs notice was taken of hers. The King more ſurpriz'd than all the reſt, did however conſtrain himſelf, and expreſſed a great many civilities to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Prince, who ſaid as he came up to him, Sir, here are I once again your Priſoner. The King aſſur'd him that he was free, and unwilling to enter into any kind of clear underſtanding, in preſence of ſo numerous a compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, he had him to the Palace, where having commanded all Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to retire, he inquired of him by what Miracle he had eſcaped death. <hi>Alzira,</hi> who was in moſt cruel perplexities on her Lovers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, did leave <hi>Balabai</hi> under her
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:150170:52"/>Womens care, and ran into her Fathers Chamber, ſhe conjur'd him to remember the promiſe that he had made her of not attempting any thing againſt the life of <hi>Ali Hamet.</hi> The King angry at a tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſport ſo unſutable to the modeſty of his Daughters ſex, did give her a kind of angry anſwer. <hi>Alzira</hi> afright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the Kings anger; It is no longer time to diſſemble, Sir, ſaid ſhe to him, our Great Prophet has already appeared unto me divers times, and has threatned me with a long continuance of dreadful evils, if I did not Marry this Prince. <hi>Bem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buca</hi> aſtoniſhed at <hi>Alzira's</hi> bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and diſcourſe, was at a ſtand what to anſwer her, when that <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> taking advantage of his diſorder, did aſſure him that <hi>Mahomet</hi> had warned him to go forth of that place where he was in danger of being deſtroy'd, that he himſelf had led him out of the Palace, giving him great aſſurances,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:150170:52"/>that he ſhould ere long be happy with a Princeſs of the Blood of the <hi>Cherifs,</hi> that he was not return'd to <hi>Feſs</hi> but by order of that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, and finally, that he did hope that having obey'd unto all that had been preſcribed to him, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet</hi> would take care of the reſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bembuca,</hi> who was a Perſon that did never give credit to Miracles, any further than they agreed with his intereſts, gave the two Lovers to underſtand that it would be a great preſumption to oppoſe the Decrees of Heaven: But that for his part, he durſt not give his conſent unto that Mariage, until the Prophet had firſt given him to underſtand his pleaſure therein: <hi>Alzira</hi> was going to reply, but the King did interrupt her, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that after ſo much fatigue, <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> might ſtand in need of reſt, and under that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, he gave order to one of his Officers, to conduct him to
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:150170:53"/>a certain Appartment which he nam'd. They were thus all three ſeparated. The King extreamly ſurpriz'd, <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> paſſionately in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amour'd, and the Princeſs divided between hope and fear. So ſoon as ſhe was return'd into her Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, ſhe paſſed into <hi>Balabai</hi>'s, where ſhe found the Prince of <hi>Feſs,</hi> who who was in vain tormenting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to chear up his Wife, who was become very much out of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour ever ſince her recovery from her ſwoon. The Prince intreated his Sifter to make uſe of all the power that ſhe had over <hi>Balabai,</hi> to oblige her to change her hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour. <hi>Alzira,</hi> who was wholly taken up with her Love, did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to her Brother to do what he deſir'd, and at the ſame time did let him know that it concern'd his honour to take a ſpecial care of <hi>Ali Hamet,</hi> and above all to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent that the King, through his Councils advice, ſhould take any
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:150170:53"/>violent reſolutions againſt that ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Prince. <hi>Balabai</hi> conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the diſorders of her heart, did alſo intreat the Prince to be near the King to diſcover his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, and did pretend to do out of complaiſance to <hi>Alzira,</hi> that which ſhe did through that intereſt which ſhe had in the perſon of <hi>Ali Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Prince, who had no thoughts but to pleaſe thoſe two Perſons that were ſo dear unto him, went forth to meet with the King. <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labai,</hi> finding her ſelf alone with <hi>Alzira,</hi> let fall thoſe tears which with much adoe ſhe had kept in, in the Princes preſence. Sympathiſe, deareſt Princeſs, <hi>ſaid ſhe to her,</hi> with me in the moſt ſenſible ſorrow that ever was felt. You know better than any one elſe, the ſtrong paſſion which I had for <hi>Ali Hamet,</hi> even from the very firſt moment that I did ſee him; we have
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:150170:54"/>thought him dead, and you may remember how ſenſible I was of his loſs. All my affliction did not take away thoſe few charms which have cauſed my misfortune. The Prince of <hi>Feſs</hi> found me to his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, you had the goodneſs to ſpeak to me in his behalf, my va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity rather than my love did make me condeſcend to his intreaties; I have given him my hand, and my faith, being prepoſſeſt that <hi>Ali Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met</hi> was no longer living. Mean time the Heavens have taken care to preſerve a life ſo precious to me, you have ſeen him as well as I, all my ſenſes have withdrawn them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in beholding that dear Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, my heart aſhamed of its trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery hath abandoned me, and it ſeems as if I had returned from my Swoon but to be the more ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of my misfortunes; for what ſhall become of me, if I cannot lay aſide my affections, nor defend my ſelf of thoſe engagements that I am
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:150170:54"/>concern'd in with the Prince of <hi>Feſs?</hi> In this extremity, I expect no ſuccour but from you, moſt dear Princeſs, you ever did take pity of my weakneſs, with your favour continue your bounty to me in this occaſion, and give me ſome comfortable advice. Counſels are uſeleſs, reply'd <hi>Alzira</hi> coldly, when that our duty does preſcribe us what we ought to do; you know yours, follow it, that is all the Counſel that can be given you. <hi>Alzira</hi> not being able to maintain any longer a Conference that wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her Love, would have retir'd in ending theſe Words; but <hi>Bala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bai,</hi> who was melting into tears, being ſtartled at ſo harſh an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, caſt her ſelf about the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes neck, intreating her not to abandon her, and to remember that ſhe had always honoured her with her affection. I muſt confeſs to you, reply'd <hi>Alzira,</hi> that your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude does ſurprize me, your
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:150170:55"/>Prince forgetting what you are, does make choice of you to raiſe you to an honour unto which you could never have pretended. The King at my requeſt conſents to it, for which you have return'd me thanks; and now through an unruly paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, you are asking of me advices againſt my own Brother, and ſuch as would deſtroy my own work. When that our paſſions grow un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, our reaſon muſt be of power to ſuppreſs them, before they ever come to be able of obliging us to act any thing againſt our own honour. Alas! reply'd <hi>Balabai,</hi> it well appears that you know not Love, it is a Tyrant who acts but by Caprichios, he neither harkens unto reaſon nor honour, and he is ſo well obey'd, that very frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the heart approves of thoſe things which reaſon condemns. This converſation had laſted longer yet, if the Prince of <hi>Feſs</hi> had not come in, who informed them that the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:150170:55"/>King had newly reſolv'd the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage between <hi>Alzira</hi> and <hi>Ali Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met,</hi> on condition that he ſhould renounce all his pretentions on the Kingdoms of <hi>Feſs</hi> and <hi>Morocco;</hi> he beg'd their Pardon that he could ſtay no longer, becauſe that he was going to propoſe it to <hi>Ali Hamet,</hi> as from his Father; and ſo he preſently went out. This di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feourſe did ſurpriſe the Princeſs and <hi>Balabai,</hi> in two different man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. They obſerv'd each other, endeavouring to conceal from one another the motions of joy and of rage which theſe news did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce in their Souls. Mean time, as it is more difficult to conceal a deſpair than a joy, <hi>Balabai</hi> lifting up her Eyes to Heaven, Great <hi>Alla! ſaid ſhe,</hi> can it be poſſible that <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> ſhould eſpouſe my Princeſs? Cruel Fates! what would you have of me? Am I not miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable enough already, in loving a Prince without hopes of ever poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſing
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:150170:56"/>him? Muſt I, in loſing him, loſe alſo that Perſon which is dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to me in the World? Yes, my dear Princeſs, continu'd ſhe, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſing her ſelf to <hi>Alzira;</hi> I am ſo little Miſtriſs of my ſelf, that in ſpight of all the obligations I owe you, I feel that it were impoſſible for me to hinder my ſelf from ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting you, if you ſhould eſpouſe my Lover: But I create chimerical ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours to my ſelf; you will never conſent to that Marriage, the Match is too unequal, and it is to be believed that our great Prophet who has taken care of your life does reſerve you to ſome great Empire. Alas! reply'd <hi>Alzira,</hi> diſſembling her joy, Perſons of my rank never Marry by their own choice, we are the States Victims, and we have but the ſatisfaction to obey with a good grace unto our Parents Wills. Could you, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued <hi>Balabai,</hi> obey with a good grace in ſuch a like occaſion?
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:150170:56"/>And would you be ſo cruel as to eſpouſe a Man ſo indifferent unto you, and which you know I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore? That you adore, interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Alzira,</hi> do you remember that you ſpeak unto your Husbands Siſter? A Perſon that has ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly paſſions, is unworthy of my Friendſhip; your paſſion, which was but a weakneſs before you had given your hand to my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is now become a crime which is moſt horrid in my ſight. Seek out for another Confident; and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that I favour you in not informing the Prince of your trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery. <hi>Balabai</hi> would have an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerd her, but <hi>Alzira</hi> went forth without giving her time ſo to do, ſhutting the door after, that <hi>Balabai</hi> might not follow her.</p>
            <p>The Prince of <hi>Feſs,</hi> who had not found <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> at home, was return'd immediately to the Princeſſes; but having obſerv'd that <hi>Balabai</hi> was ſpeaking with
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:150170:57"/>vehemency, he ſtopped at the door, and did hear the whole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation between his Wife and his Siſter; thoſe terms of Crime, Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and Treachery, that the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs had us'd, did give him ſuch an horrid Idea of his Wives perfidiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that he had already reſolv'd to Sacrifice her unto his revenge, in plunging his Dagger into her boſom. <hi>Alzira,</hi> who met him as ſhe went forth, and that gueſt, by the wildneſs that appear'd in his looks, that he had heard all, did ask him where he had left <hi>Ali Hamet.</hi> The Prince, without an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering, went about to break open the door of his Wives Chamber. But <hi>Balabai,</hi> being affrighted at the Princes violence, and <hi>Alzira's</hi> out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cries, who was endeavouring to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him, fled away by a back Stairs, which were joyning her Cloſet, and by that means did ſave her ſelf from that incenſed Princes fury. The Princes action made a great
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:150170:57"/>noiſe in the Palace. The King that was inform'd of it would know the truth. The Prince, who was very well pleaſed with his Siſter, let his Father know that ſhe could beſt inform him of it. <hi>Bem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buca</hi> ſent for his Daughter, and after that he had expreſſed to her the ſorrow that he had cauſed by <hi>Balabai's</hi> Perfideouſneſs to the Prince, in favour of <hi>Ali Hamet. Alzira</hi> obſerving that the King had ſome diſtruſt that <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> might be in League with <hi>Balabai,</hi> ſhe did Sacrifice her Friends ſecret, having no other thoughts but to juſtifie her Lover; and to make appear that he had no ſhare, nor ſo much as any knowledge of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labai's</hi> fooliſh paſſion. The King that did find much probability in all that the Princeſs ſaid, did cauſe his Son to conſent that <hi>Balabai</hi> ſhould live, who was guilty but of an involun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Paſſion. And the very next day ſhe was conducted unto a little City
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:150170:58"/>in the Confines of the Kingdom of <hi>Morocco,</hi> where a very mean Penſion was aſſigned her. Mean time <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> did accept all thoſe terms that <hi>Bembuca</hi> did require of him, in giving him his Daughter. Yet he having exact meaſures to obſerve with <hi>Gayland</hi> alſo, he got leave of the King to return to <hi>Suſs,</hi> to get his Uncles conſent, being confident that he lov'd him ſufficiently not to oppoſe his happineſs. He had the pleaſure to entertain his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriſs before his departure, and whereas they lov'd each other with the moſt ſincere and ſtrongeſt paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that ever was, the Reader may judge how tender was their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation. <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> did promiſe her that his Voyage ſhould be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhort, and <hi>Alzira</hi> did aſſure him that ſhe ſhould not enjoy any plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fure and content till his return: After his departure, the King who would have this Marriage accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed with a great deal of Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:150170:58"/>gave out his orders to have all neceſſary things got in readineſs.</p>
            <p>While that the whole City of <hi>Feſs</hi> was admiring the magnificent preparations which were in hand for this Marriage, <hi>Balabai</hi> grieved at the ill treatments which ſhe had received at <hi>Feſs,</hi> and jealous of her Rivals good Fortune, ſhe was fill'd with rage and fury, continually thinking of ſome means to revenge her ſelf of <hi>Bembuca,</hi> and of hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring <hi>Ali Hamet</hi>'s Marriage; as ſhe came to the place of her Exile, ſhe learn'd that <hi>Taffilet,</hi> who ſince has made himſelf ſo famous by his Conqueſts, had poſſeſſed himſelf of the Territories of an Ancient <hi>Jew,</hi> and that he began to impoſe Laws on divers petty Princes of his Neighbour-hood. <hi>Balabai,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting nothing but her own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair, went to <hi>Taffilet,</hi> who ſhe found at the head of a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Army. He received her very civilly, eſpecially after ſhe had aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:150170:59"/>him, that the report of his great exploits had obliged her to come and crave his protection, againſt <hi>Bembuca</hi>'s injuſtice. And the more to engage him to concern himſelf in her intereſts, ſhe was ſo ſubtle as to tell him, that <hi>Alzira</hi> who was the moſt Beautiful Princeſs of the World, and the moſt ſenſible of greatneſs, had divers times menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned him to her, complaining of her Fathers beſtowing of her by force on <hi>Ali Hamet,</hi> who had no other merits but of being of the Houſe of the <hi>Cherifs,</hi> in lieu of giving her unto a Prince of the merit and reputation that <hi>Taffilet</hi> was. <hi>Taffilet,</hi> who was the moſt ambitious of all Men, was raviſh'd to learn that love did furniſh him with ſuch a plauſible pretence of ſatisfying his ambition; and he having already heard ſomething of <hi>Alzira's</hi> Beauty, he expreſſed much joy to learn thoſe advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous thoughts that <hi>Balabat</hi> did
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:150170:59"/>aſſure him that Princeſs had of him. He promiſed her that he would never lay down his Arms till he had reveng'd her of the King of <hi>Feſs,</hi> and deliver'd <hi>Alzira</hi> from the Tyranny of ſo unjuſt a Father. He made great advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of <hi>Balabai</hi>'s coming to him, for having given out amongſt his Souldiers, that one of the greateſt Princeſſes of <hi>Africa</hi> was come to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand his protection, and magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them the great honour which they receiv'd by ſuch an Action, and given them great hopes of recompencing them libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, they all promis'd to follow him where-ever he ſhould lead them. He marched long Journeys, and he had ſuch care of providing all neceſſaries for the ſuſtenance of his Men, that his Army, far from growing weak by its fatigues, did Daily increaſe. He overcame di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers petty Princes that lay in his way, and the news of his march
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:150170:60"/>did ſo affrighten all <hi>Africa,</hi> that divers great Princes did ſeek after his Friendſhip at his own rates. Finally, without amuſing himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſmall places, which might have made him loſe time, he ſet Siege to the City of <hi>Feſs,</hi> which is the Capital of the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, at that time that <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> was there every moment expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Celebrate his Marriage with the Princeſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bembuca,</hi> who always had a great Body of Horſe in readineſs, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſurprize <hi>Taffilet</hi> before that his Retrenchments were made, did ſend the Prince of <hi>Feſs</hi> at the head of all his Cavalry to charge <hi>Taffilet</hi>'s tyred Troops. But <hi>Taffilet,</hi> who very well underſtood his buſineſs, and who had foreſeen this Sallying forth, did ſo vigorouſly receive the Prince of <hi>Feſs,</hi> that after a great Combate, <hi>Bembuca</hi>'s whole Caval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry was defeated and made to flie, and the Prince his Son taken Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner.
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:150170:60"/>The very next Morning <hi>Taffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let</hi> ſent a Trumpet to the King of <hi>Feſs,</hi> to let him know that if he did not ſend to him that very Day the Princeſs <hi>Alzira,</hi> he would the next Day ſend him back his Sons Head in a Sack. The whole Court of <hi>Feſs</hi> was in an extream conſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, when that <hi>Taffilet</hi>'s Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet arriv'd there. The King, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving heard what he had to ſay to him, did find himſelf in ſo great a confuſion, that he remain'd a long time not knowing on what to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve. His Miniſters of State, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing affrighted at <hi>Taffilet</hi>'s threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, did in vain preſs him to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine, and to ſave his Son in ſending the Princeſs to <hi>Taffilet.</hi> This unfortunate Father was in ſo great a conſternation, that he had not ſo much power as to propoſe it to his Daughter, foreſeeing that ſhe ſhould be forc'd to depart, with ſuch Violences, which he found himſelf incapable of doing. Mean
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:150170:61"/>time, as the buſineſs was preſſing, he went to his Daughters Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and told her, that it was in her power to reſtore the Peace un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Dominions, and to ſave her Brothers life. <hi>Alzira</hi> not compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending that ſhe could do ſo much good at once, made anſwer to her Father with a great deal of ſubmiſſion. <hi>Bembuca</hi> mov'd with her anſwer, retir'd without having the power to ſay more to her; a moment after he ſent her one of his Miniſters of State, accompany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with <hi>Taffilet's</hi> Trumpet, to let her underſtand what was expected from her, or rather to force her to depart. For, after having ſhewn her the neceſſity there was of ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing her for the good of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, ſhe was placed, without heed given to her tears, in a ſumptuous Chariot, which had been prepared for <hi>Ali Hamet</hi>'s Marriage. There were Women given her to ſerve her, and nothing was forgot that
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:150170:61"/>might contribute to gain the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querours favour.</p>
            <p>Thoſe Perſons which did accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany the Princeſs did exhort her in vain to conceal her grief, and to conſtrain her ſelf when ſhe ſhould be in <hi>Taffilet's</hi> preſence, to obtain the more advantageous conditions in favour of the King and his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. <hi>Alzira,</hi> who thought ſhe had nothing more to care for after the loſs of <hi>Ali Hamet,</hi> did repreſent unto her ſelf nothing but horrour, and did ſhew by her anſwers, that ſhe was very far from buying with her complayſance <hi>Taffilet's</hi> favour. She on the contrary did attempt to caſt her ſelf from the Chariot, in order to deſtroy her ſelf, complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the charitable cruelty of thoſe that would prevent her. A <hi>Portugais</hi> Slave, who had long ſerv'd her, told her, that ſeeing ſhe was not afraid of death, ſhe ſhould ſtay to the laſt extremities to uſe that remedy, and in the mean
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:150170:62"/>time endeavour to oblige <hi>Taffilet</hi> on other pretences to defer her Marriage for ſome time, to give unto the brave <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> time to raiſe an Army on Foot, and to Fight <hi>Taffilet. Alzira,</hi> who did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect all from Love and her Lovers Valour, did approve of her faithful Slaves advice, and did promiſe to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it, being however reſolv'd rather to loſe her life than Marry <hi>Taffilet.</hi> After that ſhe had taken a reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſo conformable unto her Love and deſpair, ſhe ſuſpended all her ſorrow, to take care of her dreſs, being perſwaded, as all Ladies are, that Beauty is a great help to ſucceed in all their deſigns. <hi>Taffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let</hi> being prepoſſeſt with the thoughts that the Princeſs did love him, as <hi>Balabai</hi> had aſſur'd him, ſet his Army in <hi>Battalia</hi> to honour her the more; he went to meet her, and did receive her in a very gallant manner, with the noiſe of an infinite number of Drums and
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:150170:62"/>Trumpets; he aſſur'd her that he had not taken up Arms but to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver her from her Fathers force, and to return her thanks for thoſe advantegeous thoughts which ſhe entertain'd of him, in laying at her Feet the Crowns of all thoſe Soveraigns that he had Vanquiſhed. <hi>Alzira,</hi> who could not make any thing of that diſcourſe, made him no anſwer but by divers reverences, of which <hi>Taffilet</hi> was very well pleas'd, being perſwaded that the Princeſſes ſilence was an effect of her Baſhfulneſs and Modeſty. After this he did accompany her into a magnificent Tent which he had cauſed to be purpoſely prepared, where ſhe found <hi>Balabai,</hi> who gave her the reception, and did joy her in <hi>Taffilet</hi>'s preſence, of the happy Change which had happened in her fortune, ſeeing that in lieu of Eſpouſing a Prince without Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, ſhe was going to give her Hand unto the Conquerour of all
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:150170:63"/>
               <hi>Africa. Alzira,</hi> who had not been able to retain her tears at the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of her Lovers Name, gave oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to <hi>Taffilet</hi> to enquire after the cauſe of it. <hi>Balabai,</hi> without giving her time to ſpeak, made anſwer, that the remembrance of thoſe Violences that her Father would have us'd in <hi>Ali Hamet's</hi> behalf, did doubtleſs draw thoſe tears from her. <hi>Taffilet,</hi> being at this tranſported with an amorous Zeal, did ſwear by the great <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet</hi> that he would puniſh that bold Perſon, and that he ſhould not think himſelf worthy the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſing of ſo charming a Princeſs, till he had laid at her Feet the Head of <hi>Ali Hamet.</hi> What! Sir, ſaid <hi>Balabai,</hi> interrupting him, as affrighted at that threatning, would you retard ſo long your happineſs? My own honour, reply'd <hi>Taffilet,</hi> and what I owe unto that good opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that this Princeſs has had of me, oblige me to impoſe on my ſelf
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:150170:63"/>that neceſſity; however if that ſhould not pleaſe her, her pleaſure ſhall ever Rule my Will. The Princeſs, raviſh'd to hear <hi>Taffilet</hi> of his own accord offer to defer the Marriage, was ready to take advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the proffer which he made her, but then recollecting that by that anſwer ſhe in a manner did ask him for <hi>Ali Hamet's</hi> Head, ſhe remained unreſolv'd, rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing willing that <hi>Taffilet</hi> ſhould think that ſhe approv'd not of that delay, than to ſay any thing that might advance her Lovers Ruine. <hi>Taffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let</hi> thinking that the Princeſs would declare her mind unto <hi>Balabai,</hi> did aſſure her that he was going to ſend back her Brother the Prince, and ſo went out. So ſoon as <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labai</hi> found her ſelf alone with the Princeſs, ſhe caſt her ſelf down at her Feet, to conjure her to divert <hi>Taffilet's</hi> cruel deſigns, and to give her Hand to that Prince without any further delay, leſt that he
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:150170:64"/>ſhould endeavour to give her ſome marks of his Love and Valour at <hi>Ali Hamet's</hi> coſt, who might be ſurpriz'd by a Victorious Army, if the Princeſs had not the goodneſs to ſtop this Conquerour. You queſtion not, continued ſhe, but that that violent paſſion which I have for <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> has en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged me to require <hi>Taffilet's</hi> aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, to prevent your Marriage. But I do confeſs to you that your particular intereſt hath alſo very much contributed in making me take that reſolution, through the Honour and great advantages that will accrew unto you thereby, when throughout the whole Earth it will be ſaid, that after that the moſt famous <hi>Taffilet</hi> had vanquiſhed all <hi>Africa,</hi> he has laid ſo many Crowns at your Feet, and has terminated all his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts with the poſſeſſion of your Heart. Live happy with that worthy Spouſe, enjoy long your
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:150170:64"/>proſperity, and only prevent that the ſame Hand which I have Arm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to procure unto you ſo much good, ſerve not to deſtroy my Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, who I love a thouſand times more than my life. <hi>Alzira</hi> affright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at her Rivals tranſport, percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that it was very neceſſary to diſſemble with her, did tell her that ſhe had a moſt particular eſteem for <hi>Taffilet,</hi> and promis'd without doing her ſelf any great violence therein, that ſhe ſhould never require any thing from him againſt <hi>Ali Hamet. Balabai,</hi> who was not ſatisfied with that anſwer, was continuing her requeſt, when that one of <hi>Taffilet's</hi> Officers en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd the Tent, who was ſent by his Maſter to Compliment <hi>Alzira</hi> on the Death of her Brother, and to aſſure her that he had no hand in the buſineſs; that Prince ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been kill'd as he was return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Feſs,</hi> by a Vanguard who had Charg'd him unknown. Theſe
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:150170:65"/>news did variouſly ſurprize the two Princeſſes. For <hi>Alzira</hi> was extreamly afflicted at the Death of her Brother, and <hi>Balabai,</hi> who look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on that Prince as on an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacle unto that ſtrong paſſion which ſhe had for <hi>Ali Hamet,</hi> did from that moment flatter her ſelf, that ſhe ſhould ere long be happy. Mean time <hi>Taffilet</hi> did make ſo good uſe of that conſternation in which <hi>Bembuca,</hi> and the inhabitants of <hi>Feſs,</hi> were, that he made himſelf Maſter of that Place, ſtill declaring, that he would not alter any thing; he alſo perſwaded <hi>Bembuca</hi> that he had no hand in the Prince his Sons misfortune, and did aſſure him that he would retire out of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Feſs</hi> ſo ſoon as he had Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the Princeſs. <hi>Bembuca</hi> being deceived by thoſe diſcourſes, did Write to the Princeſs, and after that he had conjur'd her by all the tender affection which he had for her, to defer no longer the giving
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:150170:65"/>of her Hand unto the famous <hi>Taffilet,</hi> he alſo made uſe of his Paternal authority to command her to do it. <hi>Taffilet</hi> himſelf did car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry this Letter to <hi>Alzira;</hi> but that Princeſs, who did find a certain kind of conſolation in the death of her Brother, ſeeing that it helped her with a pretence of bewailing her own ſorrows, did intreat <hi>Taffilet</hi> to afford her two Days to dry up her tears. <hi>Taffilet,</hi> who did affect a very great ſubmiſſion unto <hi>Alzi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi>'s Will and Pleaſure, did conſent to her deſires, and did even aſſure her that he had reſolv'd to gain her Heart by his obedience and ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but that the King had thought it fit to defer no longer their Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage.</p>
            <p>While that <hi>Taffilet</hi> was diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of all things in a readineſs to Eſpouſe <hi>Alzira</hi> with all the pomp and magnificence that he could think on, that Princeſs, who did deteſt her Fathers weakneſs, did
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:150170:66"/>melt into tears, and reſolv'd to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy her ſelf, before the term which had been granted her were come. The <hi>Portugues</hi> Slave, who did never abandon her, did in vain indeavour to make her change her reſolution. But the Princeſs did conjure her not to mention any more to her the living without <hi>Ali Hamet,</hi> and ſhe did ſo work upon the Spirit of this faithful Slave with her tears and ſobs, that ſhe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd to die with her. They pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to open their Veins, and to render to each other that recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Cruel Office. The night ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them the moſt fit time to execute their violent deſign, they did reſolve to ſtay till the Sun were ſet, and embraced one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, very well ſatisfied with that reſolution which they had newly taken. A <hi>Jew, Portugues</hi>-born, who was an Officer in <hi>Taffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets</hi> Troops, and that accidentally did Command that Day the Guard
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:150170:66"/>that was at the Princeſſes Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber door, did over hear their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, by reaſon that the Princeſs, who ſpoke <hi>Portugues</hi> to her Slave, not thinking that that Language would be underſtood by any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, had not been ſo cautious as to ſpeak low. This Officer being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maz'd at this Tragical deſign, was mov'd with a ſenſe of Compaſſion, and did reſolve either to ſave the Princeſs or to loſe himſelf. A lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle time after, he enter'd her Chamber, as if to ask her for ſome orders. <hi>Alzira</hi> did mildly recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to him, that no Perſon ſhould approach her Tent till the next Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, becauſe that ſhe was very ſleepy, and was deſirous to go ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to Bed. The <hi>Jew,</hi> who had Wit, looked fixedly on her, and feign'd to have juſt then diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſomething of extraordinary in her Face. Then did he ſpeak <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues,</hi> and told the Princeſs, that ſhe was threatned with a moſt Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:150170:67"/>accident, but that if ſhe could avoid it, ſhe would be fill'd with content, and in a ſhort time would find her ſelf the moſt happy Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs in the whole World. <hi>Alzira</hi> ſtartled at ſo ſurpriſing a diſcourſe, did admire this Strangers wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful knowledge, and ask'd him, with tears in her Eyes, if it would be as eaſie for him to inform her how ſhe ſhould attain to that happineſs which he promis'd her, as it had been for him to gueſs at the acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent with which ſhe was threatned. I ſhall not find any thing diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult to ſerve you, reply'd the <hi>Jew,</hi> and ſeeing that you have ſuch an averſion againſt <hi>Taffilet,</hi> I offer to have you to a Port that is but a Mile diſtant from this Place, and from thence I ſhall conduct you to <hi>Oran,</hi> which is the neareſt City, and that belongs to the <hi>Spaniards:</hi> Mean time things may have a new Face, and I promiſe you, that if you will follow my advice, you
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:150170:67"/>will ſoon enjoy that happineſs which I have already foretold you. <hi>Alzira</hi> mov'd at a diſcourſe which flatter'd her Love and Hopes, durſt not however truſt to a ſtrangers bare Word. But the <hi>Portugues</hi> Slave, who peradventure began to repent, did give her ſuch good reaſons to oblige her to follow the <hi>Jews</hi> Counſels, that at laſt ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to do it, being perſwaded, that ſeeing he had gueſt at her misfortunes, he would likely prove true in what he had told her of her good Fortune. The <hi>Jew</hi> went forth to diſpoſe ſo of all things, as that they might make their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat without a ſurpriſal; he alſo ſent a conſiderable Perſon to the Port, to make ſure of a Barque, and a while after he return'd into <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zira</hi>'s Chamber, who he found ready to undertake all things. She preſented him with a rich Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond, and after that ſhe had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted from him with a thouſand
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:150170:68"/>Oaths, that he ſhould not betray her, ſhe went forth, followed by her Slave, and came to the Port, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out complaint of the length of the way, though ſhe had gone on Foot. The fear which they had of being ſurpriz'd, did oblige them to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bark haſtily on the firſt Veſſel they met with: So ſoon as they were embark'd, the <hi>Jew,</hi> who had not betray'd <hi>Taffilet,</hi> but in order to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the Princeſs, who had appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo charming to him, had the boldneſs to mention his Love to her, and to propoſe to her, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire with him into <hi>Europe,</hi> where he aſſur'd her that ſhe ſhould live in a private condition a thouſand times more happy than all the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frican</hi> Princeſſes. <hi>Alzira</hi> diſdain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo inſolent a propoſition, did reproach his perfidiouſneſs to him in very outragious terms, and ſhe did ſo diſturb the Mariners through her tears and outcries, who could not underſtand one another at their
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:150170:68"/>Work, that they threatned to put her in Chains. <hi>Alzira,</hi> not daunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at their threatnings, gave them all the Jewls which ſhe had taken along with her, to appeaſe them; and perceiving that thoſe libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities did make them more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectuous, ſhe did exhort them, ſhewing them the <hi>Jew,</hi> to Chain up that Villain, who had betrayed her; and did ſpeak to them with ſo much aſſurance, that they deferr'd not the obeying of her. But judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by <hi>Alzira</hi>'s extream Beauty, that in the Sale of her they might get a conſiderable Sum, they reſolv'd to conduct her to <hi>Tangire,</hi> which belongs to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> left that if they ſhould carry her into any Port of <hi>Africa,</hi> ſhe ſhould be known, and they puniſhed. They did not alter a reſolution ſo conformable unto their avarice, and the next Day being arriv'd at <hi>Tangire,</hi> they expoſed to Sale the Princeſs of <hi>Feſs,</hi> the <hi>Portugues</hi> Slave, and the
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:150170:69"/>
               <hi>Jew.</hi> The Care that the perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Mariners did take in ſetting forth <hi>Alzira</hi>'s Beauty, and the greatneſs of her Birth, though they knew her not, did invite di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men to go to ſee her. They all found her ſo Charming, that through the Emulation which her Beauty gave them, they did offer an exceſſive Sum for her, and yet thoſe inſatiate fellows would not be ſatisfied with it, which cauſed ſome diſorder. The Governour of <hi>Tangire</hi> was at that time gone into <hi>England,</hi> and had left to Command in his place the Count <hi>Talbor,</hi> who was a very experienced Souldier, the ſame who had been Slave unto <hi>Ali Hamet.</hi> This Commander being informed of that Slaves Beauty, and of the exorbitant rate that her Maſters would ſell her at, gave order that ſhe ſhould be brought to him, that he might judge of the buſineſs. The Count, who had divers times
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:150170:69"/>ſeen <hi>Alzira</hi> in the Palace of <hi>Feſs,</hi> did eaſily know her again, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main'd in an extream ſurpriſal at the ſeeing her, in a condition ſo different from her own. He endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to aſſure himſelf better of it, in ſpeaking <hi>Portugues</hi> to her, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving heard that the Princeſs of <hi>Feſs</hi> did know that Language. <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zira,</hi> who had a confus'd Idea of having formerly ſeen elſe-where the Count <hi>Talbor,</hi> and that gueſſed by the reſpectous manner in which he ſpoke to her that ſhe was known, did inform him of her diſaſters in few Words. The Count admiring the Princeſſes generoſity, or rather love, who had choſen ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to expoſe it ſelf to all kind of miſery, than to give her hand unto the Conquerour of <hi>Africa,</hi> did aſſure her that he would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute with all his power to ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en her misfortunes, and at the ſame time did mention to her the great obligations in which he was
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:150170:70"/>indebted towards <hi>Ali Hamet,</hi> and of the pleaſure which he ſhould do to himſelf in ſhewing her his acknowledgments, by rendring ſome kind of ſervices unto a Perſon that was ſo dear unto him. <hi>Alzira,</hi> who had hearkned but with much indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferency unto all this Commanders Civilities, was ſo mov'd to learn that it was on <hi>Ali Hamet</hi>'s confideration that ſhe did find a protector and a friend in the place of a ſevere Judge, which ſhe had feared, that from that moment ſhe began to hope that the <hi>Jews</hi> predictions would be found true, and ſhe begged his pardon from the Count, who had already reſolv'd to have him pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd, as well as the Mariners, who were Chained up, in puniſhment to their perfidiouſneſs. The Count <hi>Talbor</hi> having after this cauſed a magnificent Appartment to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the Princeſs, ſhe was then treated with the ſame reſpect as if ſhe had been ſtill at her Fathers Court.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:150170:70"/>
               <hi>Taffilet,</hi> mean time, grieved at the Princeſſes flight, and at the cheat which had been put upon him, in aſſuring him that ſhe lov'd him, did turn all his fury againſt <hi>Balabai,</hi> who he did treat moſt unworthily; and after that, he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded her to the number of thoſe Women that followed the Army to ſupplie his wantonneſs. <hi>Bembu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ea</hi> was no better treated; for <hi>Taf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filet,</hi> who was always ſeeking for ſome pretences to his Ambition, did accuſe him of having had an hand in <hi>Alzira</hi>'s flight, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd his Perſon, after that he had poſſeſſed himſelf of his Eſtates.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> alarm'd at <hi>Taffilet</hi>'s progreſs, and particularly at the noiſe which was ſpred abroad, that he was going to Eſpouſe the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of <hi>Feſs,</hi> did raiſe an Army with an incredible diligence, and made great haſt to meet <hi>Taffilet,</hi> who having had notice of his March, did ſave him half the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:150170:71"/>and went before him with the confidence of a Perſon who is at the head of a Victorious Army, ſurpriſing in the mountains the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigated and ill experienced Troops of <hi>Ali Hamet</hi>'s Army, which he did Charge ſo advantageouſly, that he entirely routed them. <hi>Ali Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met,</hi> after that he had done di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ſurpriſing Actions, made his eſcape with much ado, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to <hi>Suſs,</hi> unto his Uncle <hi>Gayland,</hi> who was ſo affrighted at this defeat, and at the news which he not long after received of <hi>Taffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let</hi>'s being enter'd on the Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of <hi>Suſs,</hi> that he deferr'd not a moment of Embarking himſelf, with what he had of Riches, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire to <hi>Algar,</hi> reſolv'd to end his Days in a private condition. <hi>Ali Hamet,</hi> who was leſs afflicted at the loſs of his Country than at that of his Miſtriſs, perceiving that there was no Prince in <hi>Africa</hi> of power to protect him againſt the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:150170:71"/>
               <hi>Taffilet,</hi> remember'd that formerly a certain Prince of <hi>Europe</hi> had re-eſtabliſhed <hi>Muley</hi> on the Throne of <hi>Tunis;</hi> and making ſome reflexions on all the ſtrange actions which Fame did already re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the Emperour of the <hi>French,</hi> he did think that that Monarch was the only Perſon that could aſſiſt him againſt <hi>Taffilet,</hi> which made him reſolve to paſs into <hi>France,</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire ſuccor from that great Prince. But having not met with any fit Veſſel to perform the Voyage, he went to <hi>Tangire</hi> on a light Frigat, with an intention to make uſe of the firſt opportunity to go to <hi>France.</hi> The Count <hi>Talbor,</hi> who had had already advice of <hi>Ali Hamet</hi>'s rout, did conccal that ill news from the Princeſs, and did ſtill comfort her, in aſſuring her that it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible that <hi>Taffilet</hi>'s good Fortune ſhould laſt long. Mean time, he was advertis'd that <hi>Gayland</hi> was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired to <hi>Algar;</hi> and concerning
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:150170:72"/>himſelf very much in <hi>Ali Hamet</hi>'s buſineſs, he was in a great anxie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of mind to know what was become of that Prince, when he was informed, that there was a Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat from <hi>Suſs</hi> newly put in at the Port. He had not patience to ſtay till the Pilot was ſent to him, but run to the Port to inform himſelf more particulrrly of all that paſſed at <hi>Suſs,</hi> and at <hi>Tarudent. Ali Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met,</hi> whom he preſently knew, did make him fear, ſeeing him, that his buſineſs was deſperate; the Count received him with all the imaginable reſpects, and treated him as if he had ſtill been his Slave. The Prince, after he had Embraced him, put him in mind that they were together the firſt time that he had ſeen <hi>Alzira,</hi> and did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs to him, that he was leſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned at the loſs of his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, than at the Princeſſes grief, who was expoſed unto <hi>Taffilet</hi>'s Violence. The Count raviſhed
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:150170:72"/>that he could inform him of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that would conſolate him in that Conſternation that he ſaw him, did aſſure him, that the Princeſs of <hi>Feſs</hi> was not in <hi>Taffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let</hi>'s power; and having told him the reſolution which ſhe had taken, rather to die than to give her Hand to that Prince, he acquainted him after what manner ſhe had arriv'd at <hi>Tangire,</hi> and preſently did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company him to her Chamber. Never did any one paſs in ſo ſhort a time from an extream affliction to ſo great a joy: <hi>Ali Hamet,</hi> who thought that he had loſt all, was ſo raviſh'd to have found his fair Princeſs, who was more precious to him than all the Crowns on Earth, that he abandoned himſelf to the pleaſure of re-ſeeing her again with the ſame tranſports as if he had had no loſs: and <hi>Alzira,</hi> who had not dreaded <hi>Taffilet,</hi> but through the fears that his Arms ſhould prove fatal to her Lover,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:150170:73"/>was ſo ſatisfied with ſeeing him, that ſhe thought not ſo much as to ask news of the Battel; imagining to have gained all, now that ſhe had met again with her dear <hi>Ali Hamet.</hi> The Count <hi>Talbor,</hi> who took a particular delight to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to the good Fortune of thoſe Illuſtrious Lovers, did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to the Prince the Eſpouſing <hi>Alzira,</hi> without ſtaying till his ill Fortune ſhould once again take that charming Princeſs from him. <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> being convinc'd by ſuch reaſons as did ſo pleaſingly flatter his Love, did reſolve to propoſe it to <hi>Alzira.</hi> But when that he found himſelf near her, and that he made ſome reflexions on his misfortunes, he durſt not propoſe any thing to her, and repented having had the thoughts of ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, having much leſs trouble in bearing himſelf alone his own ill Fortune, than to ſhare it with that amiable Princeſs. His courage
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:150170:73"/>would inſpire him to attempt new things to re-gain his Eſtates, and his Love would make him find out a thouſand difficulties of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming the deſign which he had of paſſing into <hi>Europe</hi> to ask for ayd. The Count <hi>Talbor,</hi> finding him in thoſe reſolutions, did ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe him to go to <hi>Gayland,</hi> who was retir'd to <hi>Algar</hi> with vaſt Riches, and did aſſure him, that if that Prince would but furniſh him with a conſiderable Sum, he might ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily raiſe another Army, and hazard a ſecond Battel againſt <hi>Taffilet.</hi> The Prince approving much this Counſel, ſet himſelf about the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuting of it; and for fear he ſhould be molified with his Miſtriſſes Tears, he departed without taking leave of her. <hi>Gayland,</hi> who not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his great Riches, did already begin to grow weary of living in an obſcure condition, did not ſpare any thing to forward <hi>Ali Hamet</hi>'s Generous deſigns, and
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:150170:74"/>he was ſo well aſſiſted, that in a ſhort time he found himſelf at the Head of an Army, accompanied with divers Officers of Merit, which the Count <hi>Talbor</hi> gave to ſerve with him.</p>
            <p>The Nobility of <hi>Feſs,</hi> who could not brook the Violences and Scorns of <hi>Taffilet,</hi> ſent up their prayers for <hi>Ali Hamet. Taffilet</hi> alone deſpiſing an Enemy whom he had already beaten, went againſt him at the head of his Army, where he had incorporated <hi>Bem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buca</hi>'s Cavalry, which was ſtill Commanded by <hi>Maucaden.</hi> Though that <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> had much the leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer Number of Troops than his Enemy had, he expected him Manfully, with a reſolution to van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh or to die. <hi>Taffilet</hi> did Charge him with the confidence which is ſo common to Victors. But <hi>Ali Hamet</hi>'s Trorps, animated by that. Princes example, who was in all places, did combat with great
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:150170:74"/>Valour, and <hi>Taffilet</hi> was beginning to fear the ſucceſs of the Battle, when he cauſed his Body of reſerve to advance, in which was <hi>Bembu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca</hi>'s Horſe. <hi>Maucaden,</hi> fretted at <hi>Taffilet</hi>'s Violences, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at the wrongs which he had done his Siſter, did exhort his Men to abandon that Tyrant, and take <hi>Ali Hamet</hi>'s Party, who was of the Blood of the <hi>Cherifs,</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the true Succeſſor to the Crown of <hi>Feſs.</hi> He inſtantly did Charge with ſo much reſolution thoſe that would have oppoſed his deſigns, that the greateſt part did follow him. <hi>Taffilet</hi> advertiz'd of this misfortune did deſpair of Victory, and thought no more but of ſaving part of his Men with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treating. But <hi>Ali Hamet,</hi> who was deſirous to put an end to the War, taking advantage of his Enemies diſorder, did preſs him with ſo much Valour, that <hi>Taffilet</hi> was forced to change his mind, and to
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:150170:75"/>hazard all. There he was kill'd, performing of ſurpriſing actions, and <hi>Ali Hamet</hi> did gain a moſt ſignal Battel by his death, beſides his fair Miſtriſs, and divers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Kingdoms. The Count <hi>Talbor,</hi> who had ſent on the Coaſt of <hi>Feſs</hi> a Yatch, to be informed of of the ſucceſs of that great Day, did learn with all the imaginable joy, the rout and death of <hi>Taffilet.</hi> He carried theſe good news unto the Princeſs, who burning with impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiency of ſeeing her Father again, and of joying her Lover, did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure that truſty Friend not to retar'd her from that pleaſure, and to ſend her back to <hi>Feſs</hi> that very Day. The Count raviſh'd to contribute to her ſatisfaction, Embarked her in a Yatch, and gave her one of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations to acconmpany her. <hi>Ali Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met,</hi> who was not ſenſible unto ſo many happy ſucceſſes, but in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to his Miſtriſs, did ſend a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Truſt to Count <hi>Talbor,</hi> to
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:150170:75"/>give him an account, and render'd himſelf at the neareſt Port of <hi>Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gire,</hi> there to wait for news from <hi>Alzira,</hi> who was juſt Imbarking when that her Lover arriv'd there. It would be difficult to expreſs the reciprocal joy which they had at the ſight of one another. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of their late diſgraces did contribute alſo to make them reliſh with more delight the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure which they had of being to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and of thinking how worthy they were of one another. They came to <hi>Feſs,</hi> where <hi>Ali Hamet,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that he had Re-eſtabliſhed <hi>Bem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buca</hi> on the Throne, gave his Hand to <hi>Alzira</hi> with all the ſatisfaction imaginable. Soon after, he ſent Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent preſents unto the Count <hi>Talbor,</hi> and did not forget any thing that could expreſs his acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to ſo faithful a Friend.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:150170:76"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
